<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Suspention suspended. Or, The divines of Syon-Colledge late claim of the power of suspending scandalous persons, from the Lords Supper (without sequestring them from any other publicke ordinance, or the society of Christians) and that by the very will and appointment of Jesus Christ (not by vertue of any ordinance of Parliament) from whom they receive both their office and authority; briefly examined, discussed, refuted by the Word of God, and arguments deduced from it; and the contrary objections cleerly answered. Wherein, a bare suspention of persons from the Lords Supper onely, without a seclusion of them from other ordinances, is proved to be no censure or discipline appointed by Jesus Christ in his Word: ... That the Lords Supper is frequently, not rarely to be administred as well to unregenerate Christians to convert them, as to regenerate to confirme them: ... / By William Prynne of Lincolnes Inne, Esq.</title>
            <author>Prynne, William, 1600-1669.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 168 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91293</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P4097</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E510_12</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203299</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863288</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863288</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115480</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91293)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115480)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 80:E510[12])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Suspention suspended. Or, The divines of Syon-Colledge late claim of the power of suspending scandalous persons, from the Lords Supper (without sequestring them from any other publicke ordinance, or the society of Christians) and that by the very will and appointment of Jesus Christ (not by vertue of any ordinance of Parliament) from whom they receive both their office and authority; briefly examined, discussed, refuted by the Word of God, and arguments deduced from it; and the contrary objections cleerly answered. Wherein, a bare suspention of persons from the Lords Supper onely, without a seclusion of them from other ordinances, is proved to be no censure or discipline appointed by Jesus Christ in his Word: ... That the Lords Supper is frequently, not rarely to be administred as well to unregenerate Christians to convert them, as to regenerate to confirme them: ... / By William Prynne of Lincolnes Inne, Esq.</title>
                  <author>Prynne, William, 1600-1669.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 41, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.B. for Michael Sparke at the signe of the Blew-Bible in Green Arbour,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "August. 5".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115480:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SUSPENTION
SUSPENDED.</p>
            <p>OR,
<hi>The</hi> Divines <hi>of</hi> SYON-COLLEDGE <hi>late claim</hi>
Of the Power of ſuſpending Scandalous Perſons, from
the LORDS SUPPER (without ſequeſtring them from
any other Publicke Ordinance, or the ſociety of Chriſtians)
<hi>and that</hi> by the very Will <hi>and</hi> Appointment of JESUS
CHRIST (<hi>not by vertue of any Ordinance of Parliament</hi>) from
whom they receive both their Office and Authority;
<hi>briefly examined, diſcuſſed, refuted by the Word of God,
and Arguments deduced from it; and the contrary
Objections cleerly Anſwered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein; a</hi> bare Suſpention of Perſons from the LORDS
SUPPER onely, without a Secluſion of them from
other Ordinances, <hi>is proved</hi> to be no Cenſure or Diſcipline
appointed by JESUS CHRIST <hi>in his Word: That ſome Texts
commonly alledged for proof of ſuch a</hi> Suſpention <hi>and of</hi> Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication,
doe really warrant neither.</p>
            <p>That the <hi>Lords Supper</hi> is frequently, not rarely to be <hi>Adminiſtred</hi>
as well to <hi>unregenerate Chriſtians to convert them,</hi> as to <hi>regenerate to confirme
them:</hi> Whether it be a Seale of Grace or not, and in what ſenſe?
debated; and ſome common miſtakes therein rectified.</p>
            <p>By WILLIAM PRYNNE of <hi>Lincolnes Inne,</hi> Eſq.</p>
            <bibl>JER. 14. 14.</bibl>
            <q>Then the Lord ſaid unto me; the Prophets propheſie lyes in my name; I ſent them
not, neither have I commanded them, neither ſpake unto them: they Propheſie unto
you a falſe viſion and divination, and a thing of naught, and the deceit of their heart.</q>
            <bibl>1 JOHN 4. 1.</bibl>
            <q>Beloved, beleeve not every Spirit, but try the Spirits whether they be of God; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
many falſe Prophets are gone out into the world.</q>
            <p>LONDON:
Printed by <hi>T. B.</hi> for <hi>Michael Sparke</hi> at the ſigne of the Blew-Bible
in Green Arbour, 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:115480:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115480:2"/>
            <head>To the right Honourable HENRY Earle of Kent,
and the reſt of the COMMISSIONERS for the
Great Seale of England.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT HONORABLE,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE</hi> Lords Supper <hi>being commonly tearmed by</hi>
Divines, <hi>both in their</hi> Writings <hi>and</hi> Sermons
(<hi>though never by the ſpirit of God in</hi> ſacred
Writ) <hi>a</hi> Sacrament, <hi>and a</hi> Seale; <hi>yea,</hi> Gods
GREAT SEALE of Grace, and of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
of Grace; <hi>wher of our</hi> Syon Colledg Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
<hi>now preted themſelves</hi> the divine LORD KEEPERS, aſſerting
that by the will and appointment of Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, they
have both Commiſſion <hi>and</hi> Authority <hi>to</hi> ſuſpend al ſuch whom
they ſhall deem Ignorant <hi>or</hi> Scandalous from this SEALE (<hi>though</hi>
they earneſtly thirſt &amp; hunger after it, <hi>and be not</hi> actually exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated
<hi>from any</hi> other publicke Ordinance, <hi>or the</hi> ſociety of
Chriſtians:) <hi>I conceived I could not ſo</hi> fitly Dedicate <hi>this</hi> Briefe
Examination <hi>and</hi> Refutation <hi>of their</hi> Divine claim <hi>and</hi> new In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution
<hi>of</hi> ſole ſuſpention <hi>from</hi> the Sacrament (<hi>ſo much contest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
for) to any others, as to</hi> Your Honors, <hi>the</hi> preſent Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
for the Cuſtody <hi>of</hi> THE GREAT SEAL OF ENGLAND;
<hi>to whoſe</hi> Noble Patronage <hi>I humbly recommend it, ſo farre forth
onely as it ſhall appear to be conſonant to the</hi> Word of Truth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My little</hi> Treatiſe, <hi>intituled,</hi> The opening of the Great Seale
of England, <hi>was, through Gods bleſſing on it, one ſpeciall meanes of
paſſing the firſt</hi> Ordinance <hi>for the</hi> New great Seale of England,
<hi>which hath ever ſince continued in</hi> your keeping; <hi>and I have ſome
good hopes, that by the like</hi> divine Benediction <hi>on this</hi> ſmaller
Pamphlet, <hi>the</hi> Lords Supper (<hi>the</hi> GREAT SEAL OF HEA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VEN,
<hi>as many ſtile it) ſhall be</hi> opened, <hi>and</hi> communicated <hi>to many</hi>
poore ſoules <hi>cordially deſirous to receive it, who otherwiſe might
have moſt injuriouſly</hi> (by colour of the pretended Will and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment
of Jeſus Chriſt) <hi>been ſuſpended from it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:115480:3"/>
               <hi>Where this</hi> Will and Appointment of Chriſt <hi>is to be found in</hi>
Scripture, <hi>it rests on the</hi> Divines of Syon-Colledge <hi>to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate;
for my part, after many diligent</hi> inquiries <hi>to find it out either
in the</hi> old or new Teſtament, <hi>I alwayes returned with a</hi> Non eſt
inventus: <hi>only this I have obſerved in my reading, that when ever
any matters of</hi> Eccleſiaſticall or Pontificall Juriſdiction <hi>have
come to be debated, the</hi> Clergy <hi>in all</hi> Ages <hi>have made very</hi> ſtrange
Interpretations <hi>and</hi> perverſions of Scripture <hi>to maintaine their
pretended</hi> Divine Authority. <hi>What</hi> ridiculous Inferences <hi>the</hi>
Popes <hi>of</hi> Rome, <hi>with their</hi> Paraſites <hi>have publiſhed in print to
ſupport their uſurped</hi> Antichriſtian ſupremacy over all Biſhops,
Churches and Kings themſelves, <hi>from,</hi> Thou art Peter; ariſe Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
kill and eat; Lanch out into the deep; Feed my ſheepe; God
made two great lights; Behold, here are two ſwords: Ye ſhall
find an Aſſe and a Colt tyed, looſe them and bring them hither:
Tell it to the Church, &amp;c. <hi>is known to all who peruſe their Books of
this controverſie; Whether ſome of our</hi> Divines <hi>have not incurred
the like</hi> ſoleciſmes, <hi>and made almoſt as</hi> groſe Miſapplications of
Scripture <hi>as they, in maintenance of their</hi> new Church-govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
and Diſcipline, <hi>I ſubmit to the determination of ſuch who
without partiality have peruſed their la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> Diſcourſes <hi>of that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject:
For my part, having neither any</hi> private intereſt <hi>nor</hi> Deſign
<hi>to</hi> misbyas <hi>my</hi> judgment,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3. 8</note> 
               <hi>I</hi> 
               <hi rend="sup">a</hi> can (<hi>I dare</hi>) do nothing againſt the
Truth, but for the Truth <hi>in this preſent</hi> controverſie. <hi>My</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiall
debate <hi>whereof, though it may diſpleaſe ſome, will I truſt
conduce much to the</hi> ſettlement <hi>of our</hi> publike peace (<hi>which the
unhappy</hi> controverſies about Church-government <hi>have disturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed)
and find</hi> acceptance <hi>with all</hi> lovers of Truth <hi>in generall, and</hi>
your Honours <hi>in particular, from the hands</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Of your Devoted Servant,
WILLIAM PRYNNE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115480:3"/>
            <head>SUSPENTION SUSPENDED.
OR,
SYON-COLLEDGE Claime of the Power of Suſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
Scandalous perſons from the Lords Supper by the Will and
Appointment of JESUS CHRIST, and Authority derived to
Church-Officers from him, Examined, Diſcuſſed, Refuted
by the Word of GOD.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>EE Read, that one one of the firſt and fierceſt conte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations
which brake out among Chriſts owne Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,
even when he ſent them out to Preach, and
when he was about to inſtitute the Lords Supper, was
concerning Eccleſiaſticall Juriſdiction,<note n="a" place="margin">Luke 9. 46. cap. 22. 24, 25 26. Mat. 20. 20. to 29. Mark 10. 35. to 46.</note> 
               <hi>which of them
ſhould be the greateſt:</hi> which though then ſeverely check<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
and determined by Chriſt himſelfe, yet I know not
by what unhappy uninterrupted ſucceſſion it hath di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed
the peace of the Church and whole Chriſtian world, more or leſſe,
in all ſucceeding Ages; and in this laſt Age of ours, as much or more then
in any precedent Century whatſoever; the wiſdome of our wiſeſt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours,
united altogether in our greateſt and wiſeſt Counſell, the high
Court of Parliament, being unable to quiet and conjure downe this ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious,
reſtleſſe ſpirit of Domination and contention about Eccleſiaſticall
Juriſdiction, ſtill predominating in the Clergy.</p>
            <p>To inſtance but in one particular: The Parliament, after long and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
debate, was pleaſed to approve and ſet up a <hi>Presbyteriall Government</hi> in
our Church, and at the Clergies extraordinary importunity, in a pruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall
way, to give <hi>Ministers and Presbyteries power, to keep ignorant and ſcandalous
perſons from the Lords Supper,</hi> confining them to a <hi>particular enumera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion of ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals,</hi>
not leaving it <hi>arbitrary and indefinite;</hi> inveſting them with this autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
not <hi>as a Juriſdiction bequeathed to them by the will and appointment of Jeſus
Chriſt,</hi> being not ſatisfied in their conſciences, that Chriſt had given them
any ſuch divine power in his Word, but as an <hi>authority derived to them by Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance
of Parliament and humane institution,</hi> without declaring it to be of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
right.</p>
            <p>The Miniſters of <hi>London, Westminster,</hi> and within the Lines of Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication,
not ſatisfied with this <hi>New</hi> indulged Juriſdiction, meeting at <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115480:4"/>
Colledge, June</hi> 9. 1646. agreed upon certaine <hi>Conſiderations and Cautions,</hi>
which they ſoon after publiſhed in print<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wherein (contrary to the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
intention</hi> and <hi>Ordinances</hi>) they profeſſedly claime this <hi>new authority,</hi> and
the exerciſe thereof by a <hi>Divine institution,</hi> and <hi>from Jeſus Chriſt himſelfe,</hi> not
from the <hi>Parliaments grant:</hi> witneſſe this paſſage, p. 5. <hi>We conceive the power of
Church-cenſures, and in particular, the keeping of ignorant and ſcandalous perſons from
the Sacrament of the Lords Supper,</hi> to be <hi>in Church Officers,</hi> BY THE WILL
AND APPOINTMENT OF JESUS CHRIST, AND FROM
HIM THEY RECEIVE THEIR OFFICE AND AUTHORITY.
Upon which ground they further Remonſtrate; <hi>That the Ordinances</hi> (touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Presbyterial government) <hi>do not hold forth a compleat rule, nor are in all points
ſatisfactory to their conſciences;</hi> and thereupon conclude thus; <hi>Reſolving by Gods
grace to walke</hi> IN ALL THINGS ACCORDING TO THE RULE
OF THE WORD (not Ordinances) <hi>and according to the Ordinances</hi> SO
FARRE AS WE CONCIVE IT CORRESPONDENT TO IT;
(ſo as they thruſt the Ordinances and directions of Parliament quite out of
doore;) <hi>and in ſo doing, we truſt we ſhall not grieve the ſpirits of the truly godly, either
at home or abroad, nor give any juſt occaſion to them that are contrary minded to blame
our proceedings;</hi> let the Parliament take it how they pleaſe.</p>
            <p>For my owne opinion, I really profeſſe the <hi>Presbyteriall Government</hi> to be
moſt agreeable to Gods Word, and the <hi>Independent way</hi> to be a <hi>Seminary</hi> of
<hi>Sciſme, Libertiniſme, Hereſie, Errors,</hi> and a <hi>Babell of confuſion:</hi> And<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for the
Miniſters aſſembled at <hi>Syon Colledge,</hi> who agreed upon theſe <hi>Conſiderations,
and Cautions,</hi> though I cordially love and reverence their perſons; yet as
others much blame their <hi>Diſcretions</hi> in publiſhing them; ſo I cannot ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe
to this their <hi>New Paradox</hi> dogmatically aſſerted in them, <hi>That the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
of ſuſpending Ignorant &amp; ſcandalous perſons only from the Lords Supper, is in Church
Officers, by the will and appointment of Jeſus Chriſt, and that they have received this
Authority from him;</hi> becauſe I read of no ſuch will or appointment of Jeſus
Chriſt in his Word, nor of any ſuch Authority exerciſed by him (who
<hi>admitted</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">See a Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of four ſerious Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, pag. 17. to 28. <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Becons</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſme, vol. 1. fol. 481, 482, 484.</note> 
               <hi>Judas himſelfe to his laſt Supper</hi>) or expreſly delegated to any of his
Apoſtles, or any other Church-Officers by what names ſo ever diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.
True it is, that Miniſters of the Goſpell have power given them to <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct,
Exhort, rebuke the Ignorant and ſcandalous with all Authority,</hi> Tit. 2. 15. <hi>To
informe and warne them of the great danger of unworthy hearing the Word, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving
the Lords Supper; to dehort them under the paine of their owne ſoules, and
incurring of Gods judgements not to come unpreparedly to them,</hi> Luk. 8. 18. Jam. 1.
22, 23, 25. 1 Cor. 10. 21, 22. c. 11. 20. to 34. And when they have thus
done, <hi>they have diſcharged their duties, freed their owne ſoules, and are guiltleſſe of the
ſins of ſuch who will not be kept backe from theſe Ordinances, and prove unprofitable
hearers or receivers, as</hi> Ezek. 3. 17. to 22. c. 33. 7. to 17. Acts 20. 26, 27, 28. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve,
and I have<note n="c" place="margin">A Vindicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of four ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, p. 28. to 48.</note> 
               <hi>elſewhere</hi> proved at large. But that they have any <hi>Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall</hi>
or <hi>Magisteriall Authority</hi> to keepe back any unexcommunicated perſon
from the Lords Supper onely, who earneſtly deſires to receive it, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115480:4"/>
reformation, without ſuſpending him from all other Ordinances,
and that <hi>by the very will and appointment of Jeſus Christ,</hi> ſeemes a meere <hi>erroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
paradox</hi> unto me; contrary to Iſay 55, 1. Mat. 11. 28. John 7. 33. Revel.
22. 17. and other Scriptures; which (without any Relation at all unto,
or oppoſition againſt the <hi>Ordinances of Parliament, for the ſuſpending of Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
or ſcandalous perſons from the Lords Supper,</hi> by vertue of a meere Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary
Sanction) I ſhall here ſummarily diſcuſſe and refute, with refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
onely to that <hi>pretended divine Authority, will and appointment of Jeſus
Chriſt,</hi> by which our Divines now <hi>claime it for the preſent,</hi> and <hi>reſolve to execute
it for the future.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall contract the whole Controverſie into this one Queſtion,
wherein the very marrow and ſubſtance of it conſiſts, not hitherto exactly
debated by any to my knowledge.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Queſtion 1.</head>
               <p>WHether Ministers or Presbyteries Juriſdictionall Suſpention of ſcandalous
Church-members from the Lords Supper onely who deſire to receive it, without
excluding them from all other publick Ordinances (as Prayer, Preaching, Reading,
Fasting, Catechiſing, ſinging of Pſalmes, Baptizing of Infants, &amp;c.) he a divine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution,
vested in them by the Word of God, and the very will and appointment of
Jeſus Chriſt?</p>
               <p>For my part, with ſubmiſſion to better judgements, I hold the negative,
upon theſe enſuing Reaſons.</p>
               <p>My firſt Reaſon is,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> becauſe there is no direct precept or preſident in the
Old or New Teſtament yet produced by thoſe who aſſert the contrary, to
warrant any ſuch ſuſpenſion of ſcandalous perſons from the Lords Supper
onely, without a concurrent ſuſpenſion of them from all other publick
Ordinances, and that in caſe onely of obſtinate impenitency.</p>
               <p>If any ſuch be to be found, I ſhall deſire them to informe me thereof, (ſince
I could never hitherto upon my exacteſt enquiry, find out any ſuch) and
then I ſhall either cleerly anſwer, on ſubmit unto it.</p>
               <p>My ſecond Reaſon is,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Becauſe all and every the Texts produced for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate
of the contrary opinion, &amp; of Excommunication to be a <hi>divine Institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
directly militate againſt it, arguing a totall ſuſpenſion, excluſion from
all publick holy Ordinances and Church-aſſemblies, for ceremoniall or
morall uncleanneſſes, not from the Paſſover or Lords Supper onely: I
ſhall give you a taſte of ſome of the principle Texts whereon our<note n="a" place="margin">See Maſter <hi>Rutherfords</hi> divine right of Church go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, cap 3. to 15.</note> Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites
rely, that you may diſcerne how cleerly they make againſt them.</p>
               <p>The firſt is, <hi>Levit.</hi> 13. 3, 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 21, 26, 31, 46. &amp; <hi>cap.</hi> 14. 3, 8, 9, 11. He that <hi>was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected
with the plague of Leproſie among the Iſraelites, was to be</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">See 2 Kings 7. 3, 4. cap. 15. 5. 2 Chro. 26. 20, 21, 23.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhut up by the Prieſt,
and during all the time of his Leproſie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and uncleanneſſe he was to dwell</hi> ALONE
WITHOUT THE CAMPE, (for feare of Infecting others:) Upon
which ground <hi>Miriam,</hi> when leprous, was <hi>ſhut out of the Campe ſeven dayes,
and after that, received in againe,</hi> Numb. 12. 10. to 16. <hi>Ergo,</hi> he was ſecluded
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115480:5"/>
from all publick Ordinances and religious ſociety, not from the Paſſeover
or Lords Supper only, if <hi>putting out of the Camp</hi> imply ſo much.</p>
               <p>The ſecond is, <hi>Numb. 5. 1, 2, 3, 4. And the Lord ſpake into</hi> Moſes, <hi>ſaying;
Command the</hi> CHILDREN OF ISRAEL THAT THEY PUT OU<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
OF THE CAMPE <hi>every Leper, and every one that hath an Iſſue, and who ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
is defiled by the dead: both male and female ſhall be put out, without the</hi> CAMPE
<hi>ſhall ye put them, that they defile not their Campe, in the midſt whereof I dwell: And
the children of Iſrael did ſo, and put them out without the Campe. Ergo,</hi> they equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
ſecluded them from all publick Ordinances, Sacrifices, and their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
ſociety, not from the Lords Supper or Paſſeover alone; if this put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
out of the Campe were an Eccleſiaſticall cenſure and excluſion from
Gods Ordinances and ſociety of the faithfull, as is pretended.</p>
               <p>The third is, <hi>Levit. 16. 26, 27, 28. Numb. 19. 3, 7. cap. 31. 19. 24. Deut.</hi> 23. 10.
<hi>to</hi> 15. where we read of others, who <hi>for other ceremoniall uncleanneſſes and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cturnall
pollutions, were to goe out of the Campe, and not to come within it till they had
waſhed themſelves, and then when they were cleanſed, and the</hi> Sunne <hi>was downe they
might come into the Campe againe. Ergo,</hi> during the time of their excluſion
they were equally debarred from all publick Ordinances whatſoever, and
not admitted unto any other Ordinance more then to the Paſſeover, <hi>Numb.</hi>
2. 6. to 13.</p>
               <p>From theſe Texts, much<note n="c" place="margin">Maſter <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therfords</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine right of Church-go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, cap. 5 and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where.</note> urged for proofe of an Eccleſiaſticall Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction,
veſted by divine inſtitution and the will of Jeſus Chriſt in Prieſts
under the Law and Miniſters and Presbyteries under the Goſpel, to excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate
and ſuſpend from the Lords Supper ſcandalous and unclean per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons;
I ſhall onely propound four Queſtions to the Objectors of them,
wherein I deſire ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Whether the <hi>Camp</hi> of the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was not rather a Type
of their Religious Civill State and Republick, then of their Church?
and the excluſion of Lepers, and thoſe that had Iſſues, with others out of
the Campe, for theſe naturall infirmities and ceremoniall uncleanneſſes,
were not rather a temporary civill ſequeſtration to prevent infection
and diſeaſes in the Camp, then an Eccleſiaſticall cenſure of Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication
orſuſpention from the Tabernacle and publique Ordinances
uſed in it, to prevent ſpirituall infections of the ſoule, or prophanation of
the publick Ordinances of Gods worſhip? The reaſon why I propound
this Quere is, becauſe <hi>Exod. 37. 7. to</hi> 12. expreſly reſolves, that the <hi>Tabernacle of
the Congregation,</hi> repreſenting the Church of the Jewes, wherein <hi>God himſelfe
manifested his ſpeciall preſence in the Cloud and Pillar, where all publicke Sacrifices
and duties of Gods worſhip were performed by the Priests and people, and where God
met with</hi> Moſes, <hi>and anſwered him and the people face to face,</hi> was not placed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
the Camp of the Iſraelites, but a farre off without it, witneſſe the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe
words of the Text; <hi>And</hi> Moſes <hi>took the Tabernacle and pitched it</hi> WITH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>OUT
THE CAMPE A FARRE OFF FROM THE CAMPE, <hi>and
called it the Tabernacle of the Congregation: And it came to paſſe, that</hi> EVERY
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115480:5"/>
ONE THAT SOUGHT THE LORD, <hi>went</hi> OUT <hi>unto the Tabernacle
of the Congregation, which</hi> WAS WITHOUT THE CAMPE, &amp;c. Which
is likewiſe fully ſeconded, confirmed by <hi>Numb. 11. 24, to 30. And</hi> Moſes <hi>gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
the ſeventy men of the Elders of the people, and ſet them round about the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle,
and the Lord came downe in a cloud, and ſpake unto him, and took of the ſpirit that
was upon him, and gave it unto the ſeventy Elders: And it came to paſſe, that when the
ſpirit rested upon them, they propheſied and did not ceaſe: But there remained two of the
men</hi> in the Camp, <hi>and the name of the one was</hi> Eldad, <hi>and the name of the other</hi>
Medad; <hi>and the ſpirit rested upon them, and they were of them that were written,
but went</hi> not out (<hi>to wit,</hi> of the Camp) <hi>unto the</hi> Tabernable, <hi>and they Propheſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed
in the</hi> Camp: <hi>And there ran a young man and told</hi> Moſes, <hi>and ſaid,</hi> Eldad <hi>and</hi>
Medad <hi>doe propheſie</hi> in the Camp; <hi>and</hi> Joſhua <hi>the Son of</hi> Nun<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>the ſervant of</hi>
Moſes, <hi>one of his young men, anſwered and ſaid: My Lord</hi> Moſes <hi>forbid them: And</hi>
Moſes <hi>ſaid unto him; Envieſt thou for my ſake? would God all the Lords people were
Prophets, and that the Lord would put his ſpirit upon them: And</hi> Moſes <hi>gat him</hi> into
the Camp, <hi>he and the Elders of Iſrael.</hi> compared with <hi>Levit. 17. 3. to</hi> 7. By
which it is moſt cleere, that the Tabernacle ſtood without the Camp, where
they uſed both to ſacrifice and propheſie, not within it: Hence it is, in
regard the Tabernacle was placed, and all the Ceremoniall Sacrifices un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
the Law killed and ſacrificed to God <hi>without the Camp,</hi> that Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
of whoſe paſſion they were Types, ſuffered without the gates of <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi>
(typified by the <hi>Camp</hi>) that his death might the more exactly anſwer to
theſe Types; as the Author to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> thus reſolves, chap. 13. 10. to
15. <hi>We have an Altar, whereof they have no right to eat, which ſerve the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle;
for the bodies of thoſe Beasts whoſe blood is brought into the Sanctuary by the high
Prieſt for ſinne,</hi> ARE BURNT<note n="d" place="margin">Numb. 19. 3 11. Exod. 23. 13, 14: Levit. 4. 11, 12, 21. c. 8 17. c. 16. 26, 27.</note> WITHOUT THE CAMP; <hi>wherefore
Jeſus that he might ſanctifie the people,</hi> SUFFERED WITHOUT THE
GATE: <hi>Let us</hi> GOE FORTH THEREFORE TO HIM WITH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>OUT
THE CAMP, <hi>bearing his reproach: For we have here no continuing City,
but we ſeek one to come.</hi> If then to be <hi>put out of the Camp,</hi> were to be ſecluded
from the publick ordinances, and excommunicated from the ſociety of the
faithfull, as our Oppoſites moſt<note n="e" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Ruther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>furds</hi> Divine right, &amp;c. p. 179.</note> confid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntly affirme<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Then the Apoſtle
by this exhortation, <hi>Let us goe forth therefore unto him</hi> WITHOUT THE
CAMP, <hi>bearing his reproach;</hi> ſhould excite Chriſtians to excommunicate
and ſuſpend themſelves from all publick Ordinances and Chriſtian ſociety
with Gods people, which were a madneſſe to affirme. Wherefore this
Champion argument for proofe of the divine inſtitution of excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
among the Jewes under the Law, and of ſuſpention from the Lords
Supper among Chriſtians under the Goſpell, muſt be quite caſheered,
thruſt of our Oppoſites Camp as <hi>Leprous,</hi> and excommunicated out of all
their Presbyteries for an <hi>Ienoramus.</hi> If then the <hi>Tabernacle</hi> of the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation,
the place of Gods ſpeciall preſence and publick worſhip, whether
all the Prieſts and people reſorted to adore him, with their Oblations, ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices,
Prayers, was thus ſet up quite <hi>without the Iſraelites Camp, ſome good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>stian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115480:6"/>
from it;</hi> and no part thereof, nor placed within it; I may probably,
if not infallibly conclude from thence, That their Camp was rather an
Emblem of their Religious ſtate and Republick, then of their Church;
and the excluſion of theſe ceremonially uncleane perſons from it, rather a
temporary disfranchiſement or baniſhment to prevent corporall infection
and diſeaſes, then any Eccleſiaſticall cenſure of Exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication or Suſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
to prevent ſpirituall infection, or puniſh morall pollution and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
ſcandalous ſinnes; The rather becauſe Maſter<note n="e" place="margin">The Divine Right of Church-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, p. 241, 242.</note> 
                  <hi>Rutherfurd</hi> and others
affirme, that excommunication and ſuſpention from holy Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
is expreſſed in the Books of <hi>Moſes</hi> by another phraſe, <hi>to wit,</hi> by<note n="f" place="margin">Levit. 19. 8. c. 18. 29. c. 22. 3. c. 23. 29. Numb. 9. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>cutting
off from Iſrael,</hi> or <hi>from the</hi> CONGREGATION <hi>of Iſrael</hi> (that is, from the
Tabernacle of the Congregation, where the Iſraelites aſſembled to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
God) as they interpret it, <hi>Exod. 12. 15. 19. Levit.</hi> 7. 20, 21, 25.
<hi>chap.</hi> 12. 4. 9, 10, 14. a thing different from, and not the ſame with <hi>putting
out of the Camp,</hi> which moſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> reſolve to be a civill cutting off by death, not
an Eccleſiaſticall by excommunication, as is cleer by <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 14. compared
with <hi>Exod. 4. 24, 25. Levit. 20. 3, 5, 6, 17, 11. Numb.</hi> 4. 18, 19. However, let it
be one or other, it intimates and proves a totall cutting off for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
from all pubblick Ordinances, and the ſociety of the faithfull, not a
bare ſuſpention from the Paſſeover or Lords Supper onely.</p>
               <p>Secondly, I ſhall demand, Whether the excluſion of theſe uncleane per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
out of the Camp was executed either authoritatively or miniſterially
by the high P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ieſt, Prieſts, or Levites, who, for ought we read, had no ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall
or miniſteriall authority in the Camp it ſelfe, but onely <hi>in and</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">See Numb. c. 3. &amp; 4.</note> 
                  <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
the Tabernacle;</hi> or not rather by the Field Officers or Marſhals of the
Camp, ſince the command of removing them out of the Camp is expreſly
given (not to the Prieſts and Levites, but) <hi>to the children of Iſrael; and the
children of Iſrael</hi> did accordingly put them out of the Camp, <hi>Numb.</hi> 5. 1, 2, 3,
4. And if ſo, then what ſhadow of argument can be hence deduced for any
Eccleſiaſticall Juriſdiction veſted in Prieſts or Presbyters by divine right,
to excommunicate ſcandalous ſinners, or ſuſpend them from the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?
True it is, that the Prieſt was to <hi>judge who was a Leper, and to ſhut him
up in a houſe when removed out of the Camp,</hi> Levit. 13. 3, 4, 21, 26, 31, 36. but not
to turne or put him out of the Camp, which our common Law writ, <hi>De
Leproſo am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vendo</hi> proves, it being directed to the Sheriffe, Mayor, and <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall
Officers,</hi> not to Eccleſiaſticall perſons. If then this putting of
theſe uncleans perſons out of the Campe proves any Eccleſiaſticall Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction
veſted by Divine Inſtitution in any perſons to Excommunicate or
ſuſpend ſcandalous ſinners from the Lords Supper, it is onely in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
Magiſtate or people, not in Prieſts or Presbyters, as is pretended.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, whether the thruſting of Lepers and other ſuch like uncleane
perſons out of the Campe, be any infallible Argument, that they were
thereby totally ſecluded from all acceſſe unto the Tabernacle of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation,
till they were readmitted into the campe? ſince the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115480:6"/>
where Gods publick worſhip was celebrated, ſtood not within, but
without the Campe, as I have proved. If not, then it warrants no Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication,
nor ſuſpention of uncleane for ſcandalous perſons from any
publique Ordinances, and ſo is moſt impertinently produced for proofe
thereof. If yea, then it ſecluded them from all publique Sacrifices and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
of Gods worſhip alike, or from the Paſſeover onely, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſome other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
Sacrifice? If from all alike, then it warrants my concluſion, that no
ſcandalous perſon is to be ſuſpended from the Lords Supper, but he that is
likewiſe excommunicated or ſequeſtred from al other publick Ordinances:
If from the Paſſeover, or ſome other particular Ordinance onely, not
from all in generall (which cannot be proved) then it is no proofe of an
Excommunication from all publique Ordinances and the ſocity of Gods
people, for which ſome now over-confidently alleage it.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Whether thoſe who were thus ſhut out of the Camp for cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall
or corporall uncleanneſſe, were not admitted to waſh and purifie
themſelves (in the<note n="h" place="margin">Exod. 30. 18 19, &amp;c. c. 38 8 c. 40.</note> 
                  <hi>Laver, ſtanding between the Tabernacle and the Altar,</hi> as is
probable) and likewiſe to <hi>offer their Oblations, Treſpaſſe and Sinne Offerings in
the Tabernacle</hi> before their re-admiſſion into the Camp? as is more then
probable, if not infallible by <hi>Numb. 19. 1. to 11. Levit. 14. 1. to 33. Deut.</hi> 23.
10, 11. If ſo, then their excluſion out of the Camp was no excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
or ſuſpention of them from the Tabernacle and all publick Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
in it, as is pretended; Yea, then it neceſſarily followes, that ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
and corporall (much more then morall) uncleanneſſes, are to be expia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
and purged away by admiſſion to publick Church Ordinances, not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion
from them: True it is, that by <hi>Levit.</hi> 7. 20, 21. &amp; <hi>chap. 22. 4. to</hi>
16. <hi>That perſon which had any ceremoniall uncleanneſſe on him, was prohibited to eat
of the Sacrifice of the Peace Offerings, which pertaine unto the Lord, under paine of
being cut off from his people;</hi> but yet he might bring a Sinne Offering, and
a Treſpaſſe Offering to the Lord, as is cleer<note n="i" place="margin">Levit. c. 1. to c. 8.</note> by other Texts. All which
conſidered, theſe Texts much inſiſted on by Maſter <hi>Rutherfurd</hi> and others,
will prove no power veſted by divine authority in Prieſts or Presbyters, to
excommunicate or ſuſpend men from the Lords Supper.</p>
               <p>The fourth Text produced, is 2 <hi>Chron. 23. 19. And Jehojadah ſet the Porters
at the gates of the Houſe of the Lord, that none which was uncleane in any thing ſhould
enter in:</hi> If this Text (with that of the 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 26. 19, 20. coupled to it)
make ought for excommunication of ceremoniall uncleane perſons from
the Temple, and all publick Ordinances of Gods worſhip there ſolemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed,
as ſome pretend, (though here is onely a <hi>keeping,</hi> not <hi>casting out of the
Temple</hi> of ſuch, by <hi>Jehojadah</hi> his appointment alone, not by any divine inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution
that we read of, and that by the <hi>Porters</hi> only, who<note n="k" place="margin">1 Chron. 9. 17 18. c. 15. 18. c. 16 38, 42. c. 23. 5. c. 26. 1. 12. 2 Chron. 23. 4 c. 34 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3 c 35. 15 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 7 7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 45 c 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>9 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 11.</note> were not <hi>Priests</hi>
but Levites; out of the houſe of the Lord it ſelfe, not out of the Court be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
it, where we read of <hi>Oblations offered up to God on the Altar as well as in the
Temple</hi> it ſelfe; 1 <hi>Kings 8. 64. 2 Chron.</hi> 7. 7. nor yet out of the Sinagogues,
the places of Gods ordinary worſhip) yet certainly it makes point blank
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115480:7"/>
againſt any bare ſuſpenſion onely from the Paſſeover or Lords Supper,
(not here particularized) ſince here is a totall excluſion of uncleane per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
from the Temple it ſelfe, and all publick Ordinances performed in it
not from ſome alone, even in the Objectors opinion.</p>
               <p>The fift is, Ezek. 44. 7, 8, 9. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord God, no ſtranger or uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed
in heart, nor uncircumciſed in fleſh ſhall enter into my Sanctuary, of any ſtranger
that is among the children of Iſrael.</hi> In reſpect of which command, the <hi>Jewes
accuſed Paul,</hi> Acts 21. 28, 29. <hi>for bringing Greekes into the Temple,</hi> and <hi>pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luting
that holy place.</hi> Which Text, if it make any thing for excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication
(as ſome pretend, though others upon good reaſon deeme the
contrary, it ſpeaking onely of excluding uncircumciſed Heathens, not
any uncleane or ſcandalous circumciſed Iſraelites out of the Temple at <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi>
not the Jewiſh Sinagogues, nor of ſecluding or excommunicating
any baptized Chriſtians under the Goſpel from the Church though uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed
either in the fleſh or heart) yet certainly it proves nothing for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
ſole ſuſpention from the Paſſeover or Lords Supper, ſince ſuch ſtrangers
were totally ſecluded both from the Temple and all Ordinances therein
uſed, not ſuſpended from one Ordinance alone, but admitted to all
others.</p>
               <p>The ſixt Text is Matth. 18. 17. <hi>If he neglect to heare the Church, let him be to
thee as a Heathen and a Publican:</hi> that is, as our<note n="l" place="margin">Maſter <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therfurds</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine right of Church-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, cap. 8. and Due right of Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ries c. 4. ſect. 5. p. 187.</note> 
                  <hi>Oppoſites</hi> expound it; <hi>a perſon
cut off and ſecluded from the viſible Church and people of God, and all communion in holy
Ordinances,</hi> as Ezek. 44. 7, 8, 9. Acts 21. 28, 29. Epheſ. 2. 11, 12. inſinuate.
Which if objected for proofe of ſuſpention from the Lords Supper onely,
not from other Ordinances, then the meaning and ſenſe of the place muſt
be no more but this; <hi>Let him be to thee as a Heathen and a Publican;</hi> that is, let
him be ſuſpended onely from communicating at the Lords Table, once a
moneth, a quarter, a yeer, but let him conſtantly reſort unto, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate
in all other Ordinances and duties of Gods worſhip every Lords
day and Lecture day, without the leaſt ſuſpention or impediment, which
Heathens never uſed to doe, and very few Publicans: A very pretty expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of this much controverted Text.</p>
               <p>The ſeventh Scripture is, John 9. 22, 34, 35. chap. 12. 42. chap. 16. 2.
Where we read, that <hi>thoſe who profeſſed Chriſt, were put, or caſt out of the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue
by the Jewes:</hi> Ergo, they were debarred from preaching, reading of
the Word, prayer and all other publjck Offices of Gods worſhip uſed in
the Jewiſh Sinagogues, not from the Paſſeover or Lords Supper onely, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
adminiſtred in any Sinagogue that we read of in Scripture: And to
intepret <hi>putting out of the Sinagogue,</hi> to be nothing elſe but a bare ſuſpention
from the Lords Supper, without any excluſion from other Ordinances, is
a meer Bull, and miſerable perverting of theſe Texts, it being an unlawfull
act done by the unbeleeving Jewes, not againſt ſcandalous offenders, but
<hi>faithfull beleevers</hi> and <hi>profeſſors of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The eighth is the 1 Cor. 5. where the Apoſtle writes to the Church at
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115480:7"/>
                  <hi>Corinth, To take away from among them the incestuous perſon; to deliver him to Satan:
To purge out the old Leven that they might be a new lump; not to keep company with a
Brother that is a fornicator, &amp;c. with ſuch a one no not to eat;</hi> and <hi>to put away from
among themſelves that wicked perſon:</hi> From which place our<note n="m" place="margin">Maſter <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therfurds</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine right of Church-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. <hi>c.</hi> 4. qu. 1. p. 238. to 240.</note> Oppoſites in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct
us, <hi>That to deliver to Satan, is to caſt out of the Church, and to declare ſuch an
offender to be of the number of the wicked world, of which Satan is Prince, and to be
purged out of the Church, leaſt he ſhould infect the Sheep, and Christians are not to
beare company with him, nor to eat with him; and he was judged to be caſt out as a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then
and Publican, and deprived of the comfortable communion of the Saints, and of
the prayers of the Church, and meanes of Grace. Ergo,</hi> by their owne argumenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
confeſſion, expoſition, this Text enjoynes a totall excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
from all publick Ordinances, meanes of grace and communion of the
faithfull, not a naked ſuſpention onely from the Lords Supper, with free
admiſſion to all other Ordinances: But if this Text be meant of a Suſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
onely from the Lords Supper, then the <hi>delivering of that incestuous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
to Satan, the purging out of the old leaven, the not keeping company, the not eating
with him, the taking and putting away of him from among them,</hi> muſt be all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced
to this one negative act; not to admit him to the Lords Table once
a moneth, a quarter, a yeere, yet to communicate with him in all other
Ordinances every day and week in the yeer, without ſcruple or ſcandall:
an interpretation as point blank againſt the very words and meaning of
the Text as may be.</p>
               <p>The ninth is Rom. 16. 17. <hi>Now I beſeech you Brethren marke them that cauſe
diviſions and offences, contrary to the Doctrine ye have received, and avoid them:</hi>
To which I ſhall annex,<note n="n" place="margin">Maſter <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therfurds</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine right of Church-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, p. 249<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 269, &amp;c. 12. qu. 8. Mr. <hi>Walkers</hi> Modell of the Government of the Church. p. 17.</note> 2 Theſ. 3. 14. <hi>And if any man obey not our word by this
Epistle, note that man, and have no company with him, that he may be aſhamed:</hi> And
2 John 10. <hi>If there come any unto you and bring not this Doctrine, receive him not
into your houſe, neither bid him God ſpeed.</hi> Which if meant of publick commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
converſation in Ordinances of Gods worſhip with Schiſmaticall,
Hereticall, ſcandalous Chriſtians, as well as in private; prohibit commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
with them in all other publick Ordinances, as well as in the Lords
Supper; but if appropriated to a ſingle ſuſpention onely from the Lords
Table, then they muſt run into this abſurdity; that <hi>to avoid ſuch perſons, not
to keep company with them, not to receive them into our houſes, or bid them God ſpeed,</hi>
is onely not to eat the Lords Supper with them, and to ſuſpend them from
it alone; which neither the words nor meaning of theſe Texts will
beare.</p>
               <p>The tenth is Tit. 3. 10. <hi>A man that is an Heretick, after the firſt and ſecond
admonition, reject:</hi> That is, as our<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mr. Ruther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>furd</hi> and Mr. <hi>Walker,</hi> ibid.</note> Oppoſites interpret it, excommunicate
and caſt him out of the Church: But if objected to prove a bare ſuſpenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
from the Euchariſt, then <hi>reject</hi> muſt ſignifie, ſuſpend him from the
Lords Table onely, not from any other Ordinance, he may preach and
broach his hereſies ſtill, to poyſon and canker others: To which I ſhall
ſubjoyne, Rev. 2. 20. <hi>Notwithstanding I have a few things againſt thee, becauſe thou
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115480:8"/>
ſuffereſt that woman</hi> Jezabel <hi>to teach and to ſeduce my ſervants to commit fornication
and to eat things ſacrificed unto Idols:</hi> Which if it proves ought for excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication,
yet certainly makes nothing for a ſole ſuſpention from the
Sacrament, but againſt it.</p>
               <p>The eleventh is the 3 John 9, 10. <hi>Neither doth Diotrephes himſelfe receive
the Brethren, and forbiddeth them that would, and casteth them out of the Church:</hi>
that is, excommunicates them, as all accord. Which if objected for proof
of ſuſpention of ſcandalous perſons from the Lords Table only, then <hi>not to
receive the Brethren,</hi> and <hi>to caſt them out of the Church,</hi> is meerly to debarre
them from the Lords Supper onely; which the words will no wayes
beare.</p>
               <p>The twelfth is the 1 Cor. 16. 22. <hi>If any man love not the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, let
him be</hi> Anathema Maranatha: Admit this Text to containe the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree
of excommunication in the Church, as many<note n="m" place="margin">Maſter <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therfords</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine right of Church-go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, p. 372. with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</note> dogmatize, yet to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret
<hi>Anathema Maranatha,</hi> to be no more but <hi>let him he ſuſpended from the
Lords Table,</hi> is to contradict all Expoſitors, and to ſpeak little better then
pure nonſenſe.</p>
               <p>Theſe ſeverall Texts of Scripture produced by our Antagoniſts for proof
of Excommunication by divine inſtitution, doe utterly ſubvert the maine
thing they now contend for, <hi>to wit,</hi> a divine Authority veſted in Miniſters
&amp; Presbyteries not to excommunicate ſcandalous impenitent ſinners from
all Ordinances and Chriſtian ſociety, but barely to ſuſpend thoſe they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute
ſcandalous, from the Lordr Supper onely, though they deſire to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
it, without ſequeſtring them from any other publick Ordinances, to
whom<note n="n" place="margin">Doctor <hi>Drake</hi> in his ſixteen Anti-queries, in the Preface and p. 6.</note> ſome of them are likewiſe ſo indulgent, as to aſſert in print, that
a ſcandalous perſon, yea Heathen may be preſent at the Lords Supper, and
all the Sacramentall actions, and that with a great deale of profit, onely
they muſt not actually receive the outward Elements: But when we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
a proofe from Scripture for juſtificarion of this <hi>new Paradox,</hi> they c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n
produce none at all.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My third reaſon is, becauſe it is directly contrary to the very end of</hi>
Chriſts <hi>pretended giving excommunication to the Church, which in</hi>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">Divine right of church-go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, cap 4. ſect 4. qu. 5 p. 76.</note> 
                  <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi>
Rutherfurds <hi>owne words is thus expreſſed:</hi> The power of Excommunication
is given by Chriſt to a Congregation, not upon a poſitive ground, becauſe it is a viſible
institute Church, or as it is a Congregation; but this power is given to it upon this
formall ground and reaſon; Becauſe a Congregation is a number of ſinfull men, who
may be ſcandalized and infected with the company of a ſcandalous perſon; this is ſo
cleere, that if a Congregation were a company of Angels, which cannot be infected, no
ſuch power ſhould be given to them, even as there was no need that Chriſt, as a member
of the Church, either of Jewes or Christians, ſhould have a morrall power of avoiding
the company of Publicans and ſinners, becauſe he might poſſibly convert them; but they
could no wayes pervert or infect him with their ſcandals and wicked converſation;
therefore is this power given to a Congregation, as they are men, who through frailty of
n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>re mey be levened with the bad converſation of the ſcandalous, who are to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115480:8"/>
as is cleere,<note place="margin">If a little bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation in a remote Iſle have power from Chriſt to cut off a rotten member, leaſt it infect the whole body, ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> we doubt but our wiſe Law-giver hath given the ſame power to a greater bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of many vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, which is under the danger of the ſame contagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous infection?</note> 1 <hi>Cor. 5. 6. Your glorying is not good, know ye
not that a little leaven leaveneth the whole lump?</hi> Therefore are we to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw
our ſelves from Drunkards, Fornicators, Exportioners, Idolaters, and are not
to eat and drink with them, <hi>verſe</hi> 10. and from thoſe who walk inordinately and are
diſobedient, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3. 12, 13, 14. And from Hereticks, after they be admoniſhed,
leaſt we be infected with their company; juſt as nature hath given hands to a man to
defend himſelfe from injuries and violence, and hornes to Oxen, to hold off violence;
ſo hath Chriſt given the power of Excommunication to his Church, as ſpirituall armour
to ward off and defend the contagion of wicked fellowſhip: Now this reduplication of
fraile men which may be levened, agreeth to all men of many conſociated Congregations,
who are in danger to be infected with the ſcandalous behaviour of one member of a ſingle
Congregation, and agreeth not to a Congregation as ſuch: therefore this power of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication
muſt be given to many conſociated Congregations, for the Lord Jeſus
his Salve muſt be as large as the Wound, and his meane muſt be proportionable to
his end.</p>
               <p>Since then by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Rutherfurds</hi> owne aſſertion,<note n="o" place="margin">Maſter <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> Modell, &amp;c. p. 18.</note> and others concurrent ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frages
who write in defence of <hi>Excommunication,</hi> the very ground and end of
inſtituting <hi>Excommunication</hi> in the Church, is to <hi>prevent infection, contagion,
by the company, bad converſation and wicked fellowſhip of ſcandalous perſons, and to
cut off a rotten member, leaſt it infect the whole body:</hi> It muſt neceſſarily follow,
that contagious ſcandalous Church-members continuing obſtinate and
impenitent in their ſins, ought not to be ſuſpended barely from the Lords
Supper, but likewiſe from all other publick Ordinances and Chriſtian ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety,
as well as it; nay, rather from any other Ordinance then from the
Lords Supper, upon theſe enſuing grounds.</p>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe the Lords Supper is now more rare and infrequent then any
other publick Ordinance, adminiſtred in few Churches above once a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth,
in many not once a quarter, nay ſcarce once in a yeer or two, in
theſe late unhappy times, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> then but once in a day; whereas we have
prayers, preaching, reading of the Word, Baptiſme, ſinging of Pſalmes,
expoſition of Scriptures, Catechizing in many Crurches every day of the
week, at leaſtwiſe morning and evening in all or moſt of our Churches,
every Lords day, if not on week dayes too; beſides publick monethly
Faſts and frequent Thankſgivings: Now there is farre greater danger of
infection, contagion by ſcandalous ſinners in converſing with them in
theſe common publick Ordinances every week or day almoſt morning and
evening, &amp; in keeping company w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> them in private (of which few or none
make conſcience) then there is in eating and drinking with them at the
Lords Table once a month, a quarter, or happily ſcarce once a yeer, as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
reaſon will informe us; therefore we ſhould rather exclude them,
from thoſe publick Ordinances wherein they daily or weekly at leaſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe
with us, then from the Lords Supper, whereat we more rarely meet or
communicate with them; it being a ſtrange kind of madneſſe or folly to
ſhun the company of a Leper, or one infected with the peſtilence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> one half
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115480:9"/>
houre onely in a moneth or yeere, at a Supper, and yet to fit with him at,
Breakfaſt and Dinner two or three hours every day or week.</p>
               <p>Secondly, becauſe few or no ſcandalous perſons are ſo deſperately wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
or cauterized (as experience informes us) but when they come to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
the Lords Supper they will promiſe a great deale of repentance, of
reformation, and behave themſelves very piouſly, devoutly in outward
ſhew, laying aſide all their ſcandalous courſes on the whole day at leaſt
whereon they receive it, and come with ſome preparation thereunto: In
which regard, there is the leſſe danger of deriving infection from them in
and by this Ordinance of any other, whereas they come uſually to all other
Ordinances without any examination, preparation, promiſe of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
or future reformation, making no ſuch conſcie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce of abſtaining
from their ſinfull courſes on Lecture dayes or Lords dayes, as they doe on
Sacrament dayes, comming unto them with, and in their ſcandalous fin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:
therefore they ought rather to be ſuſpended from all other Ordinances
then from the Lords Supper onely, at which they are leaſt contagious,
and ſeeme to be moſt Penitent, moſt Reformed both in heart and
Life.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, thoſe who are truly pious, or at leaſt not ſcandalous, are leſſe
capable of receiving infection, contagion from ſcandalous ſinners at the
Lords Supper, then at other publick Ordinances; becauſe as thoſe ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
perſons are then leaſt ſcandalous, and moſt reclaimed in their carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age,
ſo theſe holy Communicants, in regard of their ſolemne prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations
to the Sacrament, their previous examinations of their own hearts,
lives, their ſerious Vowes, Covenants to watch and warre more againſt
all ſins, al occaſion of ſin for the future; and of thoſe heavenly meditations
which take up their thoughts, ſpirits, are leſſe capable to be infected or
polluted by them, then at other common Ordinances, to which they come
not with ſuch ſolemne preparations, watchfulneſſe, ſeriouſneſſe and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotes
againſt ſins contagion, as to the Lords Supper.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, ſcandalous perſons converſe with fewer Chriſtians at the
Lords Table, to which but few reſort, and thoſe well antidoted againſt
their contagion, then they doe at any other Ordinances, to which all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuouſly
ruſh without diſtinction or much ſolemn preparation; therfore
there is more danger of contagion in admitting them to, and greater rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
to ſequeſter them from all other common Ordinances, then the Lords
Supper onely.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, it is every way as ſcandalous and contagious to others, as dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous
to ſcandalous ſinners themſelves, to admit them to other ſacred or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances,
as to the Lords Supper. Firſt, becauſe the ſame Texts which ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend
them from one Ordinance, ſuſpend the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> equally from all others, as the
premiſes. <hi>Pſal. 50. 16, 17. Mat. 7. 6. chap.</hi> 15. 26, 37. evidence, therefore it is as
ſcandalous, as unlawfull to admit them to any other, as to the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.
Secondly, becauſe the ſame ſins, ſcandals equally diſable, unſit them
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115480:9"/>
for the holy performance of one Ordinance as another, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. 16, 17.
<hi>Pſal. 66. 18. Prov. 1. 28. chap. 28. 9. chap: 15. 8. chap. 21. 17. Iſa.</hi> 1. 10. to 21. <hi>chap.</hi>
58. 1. to 8. <hi>chap. 66. 3. Jer. 7. 7, 8, 9. chap. 14. 12. chap. 11. 11. Ezek. 8. 18. Micah</hi>
3. 4. <hi>Job 27. 9. John 9. 31. 1 Pet.</hi> 2. 1, 2. For example, drunkenneſſe, whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
covetouſneſſe, murther, malice, pride, and the like, as much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able,
unfit Chriſtians to pray, read, heare, meditate, ſing Pſalmes, Faſt, as
to receive the Lords Supper; and ſuch mens praying, hearing, faſting, is
as unacceptable to God, as unprofitable, as ſinfull, as dangerous, as damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
to themſelves as their u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>worthy receiving. Thirdly, becauſe the defect or
want of ſaving faith and Gods ſpirit makes all Ordinances alike ineffectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
to us, and unacceptable to God; we can no more pray, ſing, faſt, heare
or read the Word of God with profit or acceptance without faith and the
aſſiſtance of the ſpirit, then we can receive the Lords Supper, as is cleer by
<hi>James 1. 5, 6, 7. chap. 5. 15. Rom. 8. 26, 27. John. 6. 65. 1 Cor. 14. 15. Epheſ.</hi> 6. 18.
<hi>Heb. 4. 2. chap. 10. 38. chap.</hi> 11. 1. to 40. But eſpecially by <hi>Heb. 11. 6. Without
Faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God;</hi> and <hi>Rom. 14. 13. He that doubteth is damned
if he eat, becauſe he eateth not of Faith,</hi> FOR WHATSOEVER IS NOT
OF FAITH IS SINNE. Fourthly, becauſe all Gods Ordinances are
holy, if not of equall holineſſe; the Word, Prayer, Preaching, Faſting, &amp;c.
are all holy as well as the Sacraments, and to be kept from prophanation
as well as they, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 6. Therefore impenitent, ſcandalous perſons ought
to be excluded from the one as much as from the other. Fiftly, becauſe they
have the ſelfe ſame right to one Ordinance of God as to another, and the
ſelfe ſame command to communicate in, or abſtaine from the one as from
the other, as they are viſible actuall members of the viſible Church, to
which all Chriſts Ordinances are bequeathed, and wherein they are to be
diſpenced to all that doe unfainedly deſire them: He that commands us
to<note n="p" place="margin">Heb. 3 7, 12 13. c. 4. 2, 3. Luke 8. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>hear, and to take heed how we hear; to</hi>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">James 1. 6, 7. c. 5. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>pray, and to pray in faith, nothing doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi>
commands us likewiſe, <hi>Take, eat, this is my body, &amp;c. Drink ye all of this &amp;c.
Doe this, as oft as ye doe it in remembrance of me, &amp;c. But let a man examine him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
and ſo let him eat of that Bread, and drink of that Cup, &amp;c.</hi> 1 Cor. 11. 23. to
34. therefore all viſible members of the viſible Church, indued with
competent knowledge to examine themſelves, muſt be admitted to all Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances
alike, or ſuſpended from all alike, ſince the Scripture makes no
difference herein, and allowes us no more liberty to abſtaine from, or
neglect one Ordinance then another, nor gives Miniſters, Presbyters any
more power to ſuſpend men from one then from another, as is evident by
the forecited Texts, compared with <hi>Pſal. 119. 6. 1 Theſ. 5. 21, 22. James</hi>
2. 10, 11.</p>
               <p>From all which reaſons I conclude, that a judiciall ſuſpenſion of ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous
obſtinate ſinners from the Lords Supper onely, without excluding
them from all other ſacred Ordinances as well as it, is no divine cenſure
nor inſtitution ſufficiently warranted by the Word of God, though our
Divines now eagerly contend for it as a ſuch; the execution whereof
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115480:10"/>
they plead to be veſted by divine authority in Presbyters and Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,
but by what Scripture charter, I am yet to ſeek.</p>
               <p>The cheifeſt argument and reaſon I can meet with to juſtifie this ſole ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pention
of ſcandalous perſons from the Lords Supper onely,<note place="margin">Objection 1.</note> but not from
other publick Ordinances, is this;<note n="r" place="margin">Doct. <hi>Drakes</hi> ſixteen Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaeries, p. 6. Maſter <hi>Walker</hi> Maſter <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> &amp; others.</note> 
                  <hi>Suſpention from the Euchariſt, is a ſtep and
degree to Excommunication, and they who have power to doe the greater may doe the
leſſe; he who hath power to hang, hath alſo power to mulct or ſcourge; and why ſhould
nor they have power to ſuſpend from one Ordinance, that have power to caſt out of the
Church, and ſo to keep back from all Ordinances?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer,<note place="margin">Anſwer 1.</note> Firſt, that the Scripture no where preſcribes any ſuch ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
from the Lords Supper onely, much leſſe doth it make it a ſtep or
prodromus to a totall Excommunication, as I have formerly evidenced;
therefore Presbyters or Presbyteries have no divine authority to preſcribe
or make it ſuch, if they will keep to their owne principles,<note n="s" place="margin">See Maſter <hi>Rutherfurds</hi> divine right of Church go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, ſect 1, 2, 3, 4. cap. 1. qu. 1. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>That the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
ought to be the onely rule of all Church Diſcipline, for whatſoever is not of faith is
ſinne,</hi> Rom. 14. 13. Secondly, that where the Scripture commands a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall
Excommunication from the Church and all publick Ordinances in it,
there Miniſters and Presbyters have no more authority to ſuſpend from
one alone, and give free admtitance to all the reſt, then<note n="t" place="margin">Sam. 15. 2. to 34.</note> 
                  <hi>Saul</hi> had to <hi>ſpare</hi>
Agage <hi>and the beſt of the Sheep and Cattle: or</hi>
                  <note n="v" place="margin">Joſh. 7. i. to 16.</note> Achan <hi>to ſave the Babiloniſh Wedge
and Garment;</hi>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">Numb. 31. i. to 20.</note> 
                  <hi>or the Iſraelites to ſpare the Moabitiſh women, when God comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
them to be all destroyed, for which ſinfull partiallity they were ſeverely checked,
puniſhed.</hi> Now the Scripture commands a totall excommunication of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate
ſcandalous ſinners from all publick Ordinances whatſoever (if
from any) as the Texts forecited manifeſt, and our Oppoſites in their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes
concerning excommunication confeſſe; therefore they cannot
without ſin and contempt of Gods command, exclude them onely from
the Lords Supper, and yet freely admit them to, and communicate with
them in all others. Thirdly, to anſwer Maſter <hi>Doctors</hi> miſtaken Law;
Where a Judge by the Law (as in caſes of <hi>Treaſon, Murder, Burglary, &amp;c.</hi>)
hath power, and is preſcribed to hang the party offending, there he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
exchange or extenuate the penance at his pleaſure, by inflicting a mulct
or whipping; w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> puniſhments muſt be inflicted only when and where the
Law inflicts them, not for capitall offences, as all our common Law-books,
Lawyers will informe him; our Judges being bound by Oath, <hi>to judge onely
according to Law,</hi> not arbitrarily at their pleaſure: If then Judges may not
alter the penalties preſcribed by the Lawes of men, much leſſe may Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
or Presbyteries change or mitigate the cenſures preſcribed (as they
now contend) by the Law of God himſelfe. Fourthly, ſuſpention from
the Lords Supper onely, without ſequeſtration from all other Ordinances
together with it, is but a meer groundleſſe Invention io juſtle out the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
of excommunication ſo much contended for, and ſtrip it naked of all
its terror and Majeſty: for if excommunicate perſons may reſort freely to
heare the Word and to all other publick Ordinances but the Sacrament, yea
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115480:10"/>
be preſent at all the actions of the Sacrament it ſelfe, and be ſecluded one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
from the actuall participation of the Elements, it will make Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication
nothing formidable, yea quite ſubvert the very end, uſe and
ſubſtance thereof, to make ſcandalous perſons aſhamed.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Reply.</note>
                  <hi>But our</hi>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">Maſter <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therfurds</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine right of Presbyteries, p. 227, 273, 274, 280, 281</note> Antagonists <hi>reply; That an excommunicate perſon may</hi> freely bee
admitted to heare the Word, and ought not to be excluded from it;<note n="z" place="margin">Sixteen An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquaeries, p. 6.</note> Where (<hi>writes
the Doctor</hi>) is it ſaid that an excommunicate perſon, ſhall not have ſo much as the
priviledge of one that is without? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 24, 25. Might an Infidell heare the
Word for his converſion, and ſhall an excommunicate perſon be denied the benefit of
that Ordinance? I grant by excommunication he is as an heathen, but why he may not
have the priviledge of one that is without, I deſire Master <hi>Prynne</hi> to instruct me, and
I ſhall thank him for it: We deny not but the meditation of Christs death, the words
of institution, and the Sacramentall Elements and actions may doe much (<hi>towards
converſion</hi>) and let Master <hi>Prynne</hi> ſhew me in Scripture, why either an excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate
perſon or an Infidell may not be preſent at all theſe, yet neither of them may be
admitted to partake of the Ordinance, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Rejoinder.</note>To this I rejoyne, Firſt, that Maſter <hi>Rutherfurd</hi> cites many Canoniſts
and others in the ſame place to prove, <hi>That excommunicate perſons ought not to
be preſent at Prayers, Preaching, or any other publick Ordinance,</hi> the generall opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
of Antiquity and the Schooles; nay, he proves from <hi>Ezek.</hi> 44. 7, 8,
9. &amp; <hi>Acts 21. 28, 29. That unconverted Heathens were prohibited to come into Gods
Sanctuary, or enter into the Temple at Jeruſalem;</hi> and that thoſe who are thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municated
as Heathens, are in this ſenſe <hi>perſons quite excluded the Church and
Common-weale of Iſrael,</hi> as Heathens were, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 11, 12. elſe no excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication
could be evinced from <hi>Matth. 18. 17. Let him be to thee as an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the;</hi>
therefore Heathens, whiles ſuch, were excluded from the preaching
of the word <hi>de jure,</hi> in Chriſtian Churches and Congregations, of which
they were no members: True it is, the Apoſtles <hi>were commanded to preach the
Goſpell to all Nations and Infidels to convert them,</hi> Matth. 28. 19. Mark 16. 15.
But whether Miniſters at this day have the like Commiſſion, or are to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
meere Infidels ordinarily to heare the Word in their Congregations, is
not yet reſolved, neithr will the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 24, 25. evince it, which <hi>ſpeaks of
ſuch Ministers onely, who were endued with the ſupernaturall gift of miracles and
tongues for the converſion of Infidels,</hi> which are long ſince ceaſed. Secondly,
admit that Heathens and Infidels, if they caſually come into Chriſtian
Churches to heare the Word ought not to be excluded, but admitted to
heare it, yet it followes not that excommunicate perſons ſhould therefore
be admitted into the Church to heare the Word preached, whiles actually
excommunicated for their obſtinacy and incorrigibility in ſcandalous
ſins; Firſt, becauſe they are judicially, by way of publick cenſure and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment,
actually cut off from, and excluded out of the viſible Church,
and ſequeſtred from all publick Ordinances, all Chriſtian ſociety, for
ſcandalous offences, till their repentance and readmiſſion, as is cleere by
the premiſed Texts, and moſt Canoniſts, Caſuiſts, School men, who write
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115480:11"/>
of <hi>Excommunication,</hi> which meere Heathens who deſire to heare the Word
that they may be converted, are not: therefore during this cenſure and
their impenitency, they ought not to be admitted entrance into the
Church, or to be preſent at any other Ordinances in it till their readmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
though Heathens may, who are not judicially excluded. To illuſtrate
this by an inſtance of like nature; If a native Engliſh man be by lawfull
ſentence baniſhed the Kingdome for any crime, or a Free-man of <hi>London</hi>
expelled the lines of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication for his Delinquency till his conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
it is not lawfull for the one of them to return into the Kingdome, or the
other to come within the City, till their ſentences be revoked; yet Aliens
and Forreigners may freely enter the one and other without reſtraint, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
there is no ſuch ſentence of baniſhment or excluſion paſſed againſt
them: So a ſcandalous impenitent Chriſtian caſt out of the Church, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed
the ſociety of Chriſtians, and excluded all publick Ordinances by a
legall ſentence, ought not to be admitted till repentance, though a meere
Heathen may. Secondly, becauſe an impenitent, obſtinate, ſcandalous
Chriſtian, by <hi>Paul's</hi> owne reſolution, is more to be avoyded then a meere
Heathen without the Church; witneſſe 1 Cor. 5. 10, 11, 12, 13. <hi>I wrote to
you in an Epistle, not to keep company with fornicators; yet not altogether with the
fornicators of this world, or with the covetous, or with extortioners, or with Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
for then ye muſt goe out of the world: But now I have written unto you not to
keep company, if any man that is called a Brother be a fornicator, or covetous, or an
Idolater, or a Rayler, or a Drunkard, or an Extortioner, with ſuch a one</hi> NO
NOT TO EATE (of which few make any conſcience that preſſe this
place ſo much:) <hi>for what have I to doe to judge them that are without, doe ye not
judge them that are within? But them that are without God judgeth: Therefore put
away from among you that wicked perſon.</hi> In which words the Apoſtle informes
us, Firſt, That ſcandalous Chriſtians are<note n="z" place="margin">Which Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Ruthe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>furd</hi> affirmes, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine right of Church Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, p. 357.</note> worſe then Heathens that are
ſcandalous in the ſame kind: Secondly, That Chriſtians in ſome caſes
may keep company<note n="a" place="margin">Soe 1 Cor. 10. 27, 28.</note> 
                  <hi>and eat with the one,</hi> but not ſo much as <hi>keep company or
eat</hi> with the other: Thirdly, That they ought to judge, cenſure, put away
from among themſelves the ſcandalous Chriſtian, but not the Heathen;
which had the Doctor well obſerved, he would never have <hi>deſired me to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct
his ignorance in this kind:</hi> Fourthly, had the Doctor conſidered Matth.
7. 6. <hi>Give not that which is holy unto the dogs, neither caſt ye your Pearles before
ſwine, leaſt they trample them under their feet, and turne againe and rent you:</hi> ſpoken
principally of the preaching of the Word, not of the Lords Supper, then
not knowne nor inſtituted: Or Matth. 10. 14, 15. Mark 6. 11, 12. <hi>And
whoſoever ſhall not receive you, nor hear your words, when ye depart out of that houſe or
City, ſhake off the duſt of your feet for a testimony againſt them: Verily I ſay unto you
it ſhall be more tolerable for the Land of</hi> Sodom <hi>and</hi> Gomorrah <hi>in the day of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
then for that City:</hi> Or Acts 13. 45, 46, 50, 51. <hi>But when the Jewes ſaw
the multitudes, they were filled with envy, and ſpake againſt thoſe things that were
ſpoken by</hi> Paul, <hi>contradicting and blaſpheming: Then</hi> Paul <hi>and</hi> Barnabas <hi>waxed ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:115480:11"/>
bold and ſaid, It was neceſſary that the Word of God ſhould firſt have been ſpoken to you,
but ſeeing you put it from you, and judge your ſelves unworthy of everlasting life, loe,
we turne to the Gentiles: But the Jewes ſtirred up devout and honourable women,
and the chiefe men of the City, and raiſed perſecution againſt</hi> Paul <hi>and</hi> Barnabas,
<hi>and expelled them out of their coasts; but they ſhook off the duſt of their feet againſt
them, and came unto</hi> Iconium: Or Luke 14, 16, 17, 24. <hi>A certaine man made
a great Supper, and bade many, and ſent his ſervants at Supper time, ſaying to them
that were bidden, Come, for all things are now ready; but they all with one conſent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan
to make excuſe, &amp;c. So that ſervant came and ſhewed his Lord theſe things: Then
the Maſter of the houſe being angry, ſaid to his ſervant, Goe out into the lanes and
ſtreets of the City and bring in hither the poore and the maimed, and the halt and the
blind, &amp;c. and compell them to come in, that my houſe may be full; For I ſay unto you,
that none of thoſe men that were bidden, ſhall taſte of my Supper:</hi> Or Luke 19. 41.
<hi>And when he came neere the City, he wept over it, ſaying, if thou hadſt knowne, even
thou, at leaſt in this thy day, the things which belong unto thy peace, but now they are
hid from thine eyes;</hi> with ſundry other Texts of this kind: He might have
learned from them, That ſuch Chriſtians who contemne and neglect the
Goſpel and word of Grace when offered to them, may be juſtly deprived of
and ſecluded from them, when as others, though Pagans, may be admitted
to enjoy them, according to that expreſſe Text Mat. 21. 33. to 45. where <hi>the
Lord of the Vineyard, when his ſervants were beaten and his ſon ſlaine by the husband-men
from whom he required fruits; threatens he will miſerably destroy thoſe wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
men, and will let out his Vineyard to other husband-men, which ſhall render him
their fruit in due ſeaſon;</hi> Chriſt himſelfe thus cloſing up the Parable, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference
to the obſtinate Jewes; <hi>Therefore I ſay unto you, the Kingdome of God,
ſhall be taken from you, and given to a Nation bringing forth the fruits thereof;</hi> which
you may read fully executed and ratified, Rom. 11. 7. to 26. 1 Theſ. 2. 15, 16.
Iſa. 5. 1. to 8. This Objection therefore will no wayes fortifie our Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites
weak Cauſe, but confirme my tenets.</p>
               <p>But it is ſecondly objected by our <hi>Antagouists,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Objection</hi> 2. b M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſter <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rds</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine right of Presbyter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, p. 361, 362, 524, 525.</note> that the Word may and
muſt be preached to meere Pagans and Infidels, to convert and inſtruct
them; but the Lords Supper is not to be adminiſtred to ſuch, as all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge:
Therefore there is a vaſt difference in this reſpect between
the preaching of the Word, and receiving of the Lords Supper; and ſo by
conſequence, ſcandalous perſons which are as Heathens, may and ought to
be ſuſpended from the one, though they be admitted to the other.</p>
               <p>I anſwer,<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> Firſt, this Objection, if examined, is but a meere fallacy, and
inconſequent, the controverſie not being, <hi>Whether Infidels, Turks and Pagans
ought to be admitted to the Lords Table before they publickly embrace and profeſſe the
Chriſtian faith?</hi> But, <hi>Whether ſcandalous Christans externally embracing, profeſſing
the faith of Chriſt, endued with competent knowledge, profeſſing, unfain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d repentance
for their ſinnes paſt, promiſing reformation for the future, and earnesily deſiring to be
admitted to the Lords Supper, may by any institu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> or appointment of Jeſus Chriſt be
ſuſpended from it; when not ſecluded from, but admitted free acceſſe to the Word, and all
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115480:12"/>
other pulick Ordinances?</hi> Therefore to argue thus, the Lords Supper ought
not to be adminiſtred to Turkes and Infidels; <hi>Ergo,</hi> not to ſcandalous
Chriſtians, is a meere <hi>Nonſequitur,</hi> and departing from the point in iſſue.
Secondly, the reaſon why the Lords Supper and Baptiſme ought not to
be adminiſtred to <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Pagans</hi> before their externall converſion to the
Chriſtian faith, though the Goſpell may be preached to them, is not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
preaching of the Goſpel is a converting Ordinance, and the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration
of the Sacraments onely a confirming, but not converting Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance;
(as is pretended;) but becauſe the <hi>Sacraments</hi> (as all<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Calvin, Peter Martyr, Areti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, Jewel, Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con, Paraeus, Willet,</hi> others, and Maſter <hi>Rutherfurd</hi> himſelfe, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine right of Presbyteries, cap. 4. ſect. 5. p. 212.</note> Divines accord)
<hi>are badges of our externall Christian profeſſion; yea, ſolemne Covenants or Oaths to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige
us to yeeld all obedience and ſubjection unto Chriſt, and distinguiſhing ſignes to dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference
Christians from all Infidels and Pagans in the world;</hi> therefore not to be
adminiſtred to any but ſuch who actually embrace and profeſſe the faith of
Chriſt, and are admitted members of his viſible Church; whereas the
bare externall hearing of the Word preached (wherein the hearers are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
paſſive, but no wayes active or ſtipulative, unleſſe they embrace it) is no
ſuch badge or emblem of Chriſtianity, nor ſuch an externall Oath of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leagiance
to tye us to the obedience of Chriſt, as <hi>Baptiſme</hi> and the <hi>Lords
Supper</hi> are, which belong to none but ſuch who profeſſe themſelves Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians
and are members of the viſible Church of Chriſt. Thirdly, It is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally
agreed by all orthodox Divines, that <hi>Baptiſme and the Lords Supper
are by the will and appointment of Jeſus Chriſt, given not ſimply and ſolely to the elect
and inviſible Church of Chriſt,</hi> (certainly knowne to God alone, not to any
Miniſters or Presbyteries upon earth) <hi>but to all the viſible members of the viſible
Church, not cut off from it by a legall Excommunication, or hindred by ſome naturall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abilities,
who have a true right to, and intereſt in them, though not actually regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated
and endued with ſaving faith.</hi> Upon which grounds Maſter<note n="d" place="margin">Due right of Presbyteries, cap. 4. ſect. 6. throughout.</note> 
                  <hi>Rutherfurd,</hi>
and Maſter<note n="e" place="margin">A defence of Infants Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, part 3. p. 106. to 130.</note> 
                  <hi>Marſhall</hi> expreſly maintain, the <hi>lawfulneſſe of baptizing the children
of excommunicate perſons, Hereticks, Schiſmaticks, and Christians unregenerate,
even for the externall profeſſion of the Christian faith by their ancesters, though their
immediate Parents be Hereticks, or perſons excommunicated from the viſible Church:</hi>
Which being granted, reſolved as an undoubted truth in the <hi>Sacrament</hi> of
<hi>Baptiſme,</hi> muſt likewiſe thus farre hold in caſe of the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> That a
viſible member of the viſible Church endued with competent knowledge,
and not actually excommunicated, ought not to be ſuſpended from it for
any pretended ſcandalous crime, in caſe he deſire to receive it, ſince his
very memberſhip in the viſible Church intitles him thereunto, as well as
himſelfe or his children to <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> and gives him a right to receive
it,<note place="margin">Objection 3.</note> yea makes him guilty of ſinne, in caſe he neglect to participate thereof,
when publickly invited to receive it, as our ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <hi>Homilies</hi> concerning the
receiving the Lords Supper reſolve: which fully anſwers this fallacious
Objection.</p>
               <p>Thirdly it is objected,<note n="f" place="margin">Maſter <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therfurds</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ght of Church-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment c. 5. &amp; Due right of Presby <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries c. 4. ſect 5</note> That the Sacrament of the Lords Supper is a
Seale of Grace, and of the Covenant of Grace, as it is a Sacrament, which
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115480:12"/>
the preaching of the Word is not; therefore ſcandalous perſons ought to
be ſuſpended from it, though they be admitted to the preaching of the
Word and other publick Ordinances, elſe we ſhould put a ſezle unto a
blank.</p>
               <p>I anſwer,<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> Firſt, that the Lords Supper is by no Text in Scripture ſtiled
a <hi>Seale,</hi> or <hi>Seale of Grace,</hi> or <hi>of the Covenant of Grace,</hi> though many Divines
(without any Scripture authority) ſtile it ſo. Secondly, it is true, that
<hi>Circumciſion</hi> is once onely in the Now Teſtament, <hi>to wit, Rom.</hi> 4. 11. ſtiled,
<hi>The</hi> SIGNE <hi>of Circum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſion,</hi> A SEALE <hi>of the righteouſneſſe of faith,
which</hi> Abraham <hi>had yet being uncircumc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſed:</hi> Whence<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Calvin, Peter Martyr, Parae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> and Doctor <hi>Willet</hi> on Rom 4. Aretii Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem. Locus, 77. Ameſii Bellarminus Enerva us, Tom. 4. qu 4. and others.</note> 
                  <hi>Divines</hi> inferre, <hi>That
Baptiſme and the Lords Supper are both Sacraments and Seales of Grace, and of the
Covenant of Grace:</hi> But that it ſhould hence neceſſarily follow, that Baptiſme
and the Lords Supper are Sacraments, are Seales of Grace, and of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant
of Grace (though never ſo called in Scripture, nor yet the Paſſeover)
becauſe Circumciſion is called a <hi>Signe</hi> and a <hi>Seale of the righteouſneſſe of faith,
which Abraham had yet being uncircum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſed,</hi> is expreſly denied by<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Stapletoni</hi> Antld. p. 225. Pererius Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>put. 4. num. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Bellarminus, l. 2. c. 10. De Sacram. Remonſtr. in Apol. c. 23. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopius Diſp. 29. Theſ. 8. Smalci. cont. Franzium Diſp. 9. p. 199. Socin. de offic. Hom. Chriſt. c. 4 and others</note> ſome, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
by others, and cannot infallibly be inferred thence, for ought appeares
to me. Thirdly, admit the Lords Supper be a Seale of Grace, as Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cſiion
was of faith, yet in what ſenſe, or in what reſpects it is or may be
<note n="i" place="margin">See <hi>Willets</hi> ſix-fold Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary on Rom. 4. qu. 7.</note> ſtiled a Seale, and what kind of Seale it is, is queſtioned by many, and
very difficult to determine. <hi>Origen</hi> thinks <hi>Circumciſion was called a Seale of the
righteouſneſſe of faith, becauſe in Circumciſion was ſealed and lay bid the righteouſneſſe
of faith, which ſhould afterward be revealed and unfolded in Chriſt, and a Seale to the
unbeleeving Jewes, ſhutting them up in unbeliefe, untill they ſhould be called in the end
of the world: Chryſostome, Theodoret</hi> and others, expound it to be a <hi>Seale,</hi> that
is, <hi>a teſtimony onely of faith received: Aquinas</hi> thinks it was called a <hi>Seale, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
it was an expreſſe Signe, having a ſimilitude of the thing received:</hi> Others
affirme it was tearmed a <hi>Seale,</hi> becauſe <hi>it distinguiſhed the Iſraelites from other
people, as</hi> Seales <hi>distinguiſh one Merchants Goods and Letters from another:</hi> But
<hi>Calvin, Paraeus, Fayus, Aretius, Peter Martyr, Marlorat, Willet,</hi> and the ſtreame
of moderne Divines tearme it a <hi>Seale,</hi> becauſe it is a <hi>viſible confirmation of
Gods promiſes to his people, as Kings and other m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns Seales confirme their Patents and
Deeds, being added to them for better aſſurance:</hi> And in this laſt ſenſe our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines
generally tearme <hi>Baptiſme</hi> and the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> SEALES, that
is, <hi>externall viſible confirmations of Gods promiſes:</hi> Indeed though I find not
the <hi>Lords Supper</hi> or <hi>Baptiſme</hi> called <hi>Seales</hi> in Scripture, yet I read therein of
a ſix-fold uſe of Seales. The firſt is, to <hi>conceale and cloſe up things from publick
view,</hi> as Cant. 4. 12. Iſa. 29. 11. Job 41. 15. Dan. 9. 24. chap. 12. 9. Revel.
10. 4. chap. 22. 10. chap. 5. 1. to 10. chap. 6. 1. In which ſenſe the Greekes
tearme Sacraments <hi>Mysteries</hi> or <hi>hidden things,</hi> the phraſe uſed by <hi>Paul,</hi> Eph.
3. 9. chap. 5. 32. and<note n="k" place="margin">Decana Dom. &amp; Baptiſmo <hi>Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Bernard,</hi> with others, ſtiles a Sacrament, <hi>Satrun ſecre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi>
a <hi>ſacred<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſecret.</hi> The ſecond, to <hi>preſerve, ſhut up, and keep things ſafe,</hi> Deut.
32. 43. Dan. 6. 17. Job 34. 16. chap. 37. 7. Matth. 27. 66. Job 14. 17. The
third, to <hi>distinguiſh one thing from another,</hi> 1 Tim. 2. 19. Revel. 7. 3. to 9. chap.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115480:13"/>
9. 10. The fourth, to <hi>appropriate things, and mark them for our owne,</hi> 2 Cor.
1, 22. 2 Tim. 2. 19. chap. 7. 2. to 8. Epheſ. 1. 13. The fift to <hi>authorize and
give commiſſion,</hi> John 6. 26. The ſixt, to <hi>confirme, ratifie, aſſure charters, Dee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
Promiſes, Covenants,</hi> Nehem. 9. 38. Eſter 8. 8, 10. chap. 3. 12. Cant. 8.
6. Jer. 32. 10, 15, 44. Dan. 6. 17. 2 Cor. 1. 22. Epheſ. 4. 3. 2 Tim. 2. 19.
1 Cor. 9. 2. In ſome of theſe ſenſes the Lords Supper may perchance im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>properly
be called a Seale by way of alluſion, but yet not properly and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly,
ſince Maſter <hi>Rutherfurd</hi> himſelfe puts many differences <hi>between it and
a civill ſeale,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Due right of Presbyteries, c. 4. ſect. 5. p. 212, to 218.</note> and Chriſt himſelfe ordained it not to be a Seale, but <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance,
memoriall, repreſentation of his Death and Paſſion,</hi> as is cleer by Luke 22.
19. 1 Cor. 11. 24, 25, 26. <hi>This is my Body which is given for you, Doethis</hi> IN
REMEMBRANCE OF ME; <hi>This cup is the New Testament in my
blood, this doe ye as often as ye drink it in</hi> REMEMBRANCE OF ME,
<hi>For as oft as ye eat this Bread and drink this Cup,</hi> YE DOE SHEW THE
LORDS DEATH TILL HE COME. Now being a Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance
and Repreſentation of Chriſts Death by divine inſtitution, which
hath no Analogy with a Seale, which ſerves not to commemorate or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent
any thing, and being no where tearmed a Seale in Scripture; I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
it farre more proper to ſtile the Lords Supper (as the<note n="k" place="margin">Biſhop <hi>Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ls</hi> Defence of the Apology, part 2. cap. 13 Diviſ. 1. p. 251</note> Fathers uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
doe) a <hi>Figure, Signe, Remembrance, Memory,</hi> or <hi>Repreſentation of Christs
Death,</hi> then a Seale; which phraſe is the originall ground of mens bare
ſuſpention from it. Fourthly, It is admitted by all, that <hi>Baptiſme</hi> is a
<hi>Seale of Grace,</hi> and of <hi>the Covenant of Grace,</hi> as well as the Lords Supper; I
would then gladly be informed by our oppoſite Brethen, by what autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
will and appointment of Jeſus Chriſt, thoſe who are admitted to be
partakers of one of the Seales of Grace, and whoſe children by their owne
reſolution ought to be admitted unto Baptiſme, even for theſe their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents
externall profeſſion of Chriſtianity and memberſhip in a viſible
Church, ſhould be thus ſuſpended, excluded from the Lords Sxpper, the
other Seale, not being totally ſecluded from all other Ordinances, having
as good a title to the one Seale as the other, to the Lords Table as to
Baptiſme or the Word it ſelfe? If they reply, as uſually they doe, that it
is, <hi>becauſe we muſt not put a Seale unto a blanke,</hi> nor give the Seale of grace to
thoſe that have no grace. I anſwer, Firſt, that this reaſon is a meer whim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey
of their owne, warranted by no Scripture. Secondly, it is contrary to
Scripture, their owne practice and confeſſion; who<note n="l" place="margin">Maſter <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therfurds</hi> Due right of Presbyteries, c. 4 ſect. 5. Maſter <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhals</hi> De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ce of Infants Bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſme.</note> grant; Firſt, that <hi>the
Sacrament and Seale of Baptiſme may and ought to be given to the perſons, yea Infants
of thoſe who externally profeſſe the christian Religion,</hi> though <hi>they be not truly rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate,</hi>
yea to the infants of Ignorant and Scandalous Chriſtians, though ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate,
even for theſe their Parents externall profeſſion of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity.
Secondly, that unregeherate perſons who are not ignorant or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly
ſcandalous, cannot be ſuſpended from the Lords Supper, but
muſt be admitted to it, if they deſire it. Thirdly, that in this caſe a Seale
is not put put unto a blank, for if their very baptizing at firſt was no ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115480:13"/>
of a Blank, then by the ſame reaſon, their receiving the Lords Supper
cannot be ſo. Now that their baptizing was not ſo, I ſhall prove by Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
<note n="l" place="margin">A defence of Infant baptiſm <hi>London,</hi> 1646. (Dedicated to the Aſſembly of Divines) p. 117, 118.</note> 
                  <hi>Marſhals</hi> owne reſolution, approved by the Aſſembly; <hi>You conclude</hi>
(writes he againſt Maſter <hi>Tombes) that if there be not a promiſe of theſe ſaving
graces to Infants, in vaine are they baptized, and the Seale is put to a blank.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My meaning is indeed according to the ſenſe of the Directory, and according to that
direction I doe pray,</hi> 
                  <q rend="inline margQuotes">That God would make Baptiſme to be a Seale to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant
of adoption, and the reſt of the ſaving graces of the Covenant; <hi>yet
I utterly deny your conſequence,</hi> that unleſſe there be abſolute promiſes of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
grace to infants, the ſcale is ſet to a blank; for give me leave but to
put the ſame caſe; Firſt, <hi>for the Infants of the Jewes, was the ſeale put to a blank
with them,</hi> or had they all promiſes of <hi>ſaving graces? Secondly, let me put the
ſame caſe in growne men, who make an externall viſible profeſſion, and thereupon are
admitted to baptiſme; can any man ſay, that all the ſaving graces of the Covenant
or the ſpirituall part of it, is promiſed to all viſible profeſſors? is it not abundantly
knowne, that in all Ages, even in the beſt times, even in the Apostles time, multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes
were baptized, to whom God yet never gave ſaving graces, and therefore ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
promiſed them? for had he made a promiſe, he would have performed it: But I
ſhall deſire you a little to conſider the nature of a Sacrament, in what ſenſe it is a
Seale, and then you need ſtumble at this no longer; Theſe three things are neceſſary to
be distinguiſhed:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Note.</note> Firſt, the truth of the thing ſignified in a Sacrament; and
ſecondly, my intereſt in that thing; and thirdly, my obligation to doe
what is required in or by that Sacrament: <hi>I ſay therefore, that in every Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament,
the truth of the Covenant in it ſelfe, and all the promiſes of it are ſealed to
be Yea and Amen; Jeſus Cbriſt became a Minister of the Circumciſion, to confirme
the Promiſes made unto the Fathers; and ſo to every one who is admitted to partake
of Baptiſme, according to the Rule which God had given to his Church, to administer
that Sacrament,</hi> there is ſealed the truth of all the promiſes of the Goſpel,
<hi>that they are all true in Chriſt, and whoſoever partakes of Chriſt, ſhall partake of all
theſe ſaving promiſes:</hi> this is abſolutely ſealed in Baptiſme; <hi>but as to the ſecond,
which is</hi> intereſſe meum, <hi>or the receivers intereſt in that ſpirituall part of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,
that is ſealed to no receiver abſolutely, but conditionally; in this particular, all
Sacraments are but</hi> Signa conditionalia, <hi>conditionall Seales, ſealing the ſpirituall
part of the Covenant to the receiver upon condition, that he performe the ſpirituall
condition of the Covenant; thus</hi> our Divines <hi>uſe to anſwer the Papists;</hi> thus Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor
Ames <hi>An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>wers</hi> to Bellarmine, <hi>when</hi> Bellarmine <hi>diſputing againſt our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi>
that Sacraments are Seales, <hi>alleages,</hi> then they are falſly applyed
oftentimes; <hi>he di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> wers</hi> to Bellarmine, <hi>Sacraments are conditionall Seales, and
therefo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e not ſeales to us but upon condition: Now for the third thing,</hi> the obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
which is put upon the receiver, <hi>a lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> or tye for him to perform, who is
admitted to receive the Sacrament; this third, I ſay, is alſo abſolute, all circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
and baptized perſons did, or doe ſtand abſolutely engaged to performe the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
required on their part, and therefore all circumciſed perſons</hi> were by the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>on
obliged to keep the Law; <hi>that is, that legall and typicall admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration</hi>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:115480:14"/>
                     <hi>of the Covenant which was then in force, and Infants among the reſt, were
bound to this, though they had no understanding of the Covenant, or that administra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of the Covenant, when this Seale was administred to them: Now then, ſince in
Baptiſme there is ſuch an abſolute Seale of the truth of the Covenant of Grace in it
ſelfe, a conditionall Seale of the receivers intereſt in the Covenant, and an abſolut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
obligation upon the receiver to make good the Covenant on his part;</hi>
                  </q> IS THERE
ANY REASON YOU SHOULD SAY, THAT THE SEALE IS
PUT TO A BLANK, WHERE THE SPIRITUALL PART OF
SAVING GRACE IS NOT PARTAKED OF? This anſwer of
Maſter <hi>Marſhall</hi> to Maſter <hi>Tombes</hi> (approved by <hi>the Aſſembly of Divines,</hi> and
<hi>Commiſſioners of the Church of</hi> Scotland, to whom it is Dedicated) in the caſe
of Baptiſme, gives a full anſwer to the ſelf-ſame objection of our Antago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts
in caſe of the Lords ſupper, they being both Sacraments and Seales
alike, and ſubverts the very maine foundation of <hi>Suſpention onely from the
Lords Table;</hi> for if the Lords Supper be in truth a <hi>Seale of Grace,</hi> as is allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged,
yet ſeeing it is onely a <hi>conditionall Seale of the receivers intereſt in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi>
but an <hi>abſolute Seale</hi> to every worthy and unworthy receiver of <hi>the
Covenant of Grace in it ſelfe,</hi> and an abſolute obligation to make <hi>good the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant
on their parts,</hi> as Maſter <hi>Marſhall</hi> determines, and Maſter <hi>Rutherfurd</hi>
himſelfe concludes againſt the Anabaptiſts, in his Due Right of Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteries,
cap. 8. ſect. 5. p. 214, 215, 216. Nay more (which I ſhall adde) if
it be a viſible memoriall, Remembrance and Repreſentation of the Paſſion
of Jeſus Chriſt to every receiver, a badge of diſtinction to difference Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians
from Turks, Pagans, Inſidels, Jewes, and a ſtrong incitation and
engagement to them to many Chriſtian vertues duties, as namely to Faith,
Hope, Charity, Thankfulneſſe, Mortification of their carnall luſts, Patience
under the Croſſe, unfained love to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt and all his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,
hatred of, and watchfulneſſe againſt ſinne, and univerſall obedience
to Chriſt, (as<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Aretius, Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin,</hi> the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, and Maſter <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therfurd</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, Due right of Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteries c. 4. ſect. 5. p. 212.</note> Divines unanimouſly accord;) and if it be in truth but a
meere viſible Word, or Preaching of the Goſpel and Chriſts paſſion to the
eye, as all accord, no ſcandalous unexcommunicated perſon ought to be
ſuſpended from it, that is not actually ſuſpended from hearing the Word
and all other publick Ordinances; the rather, becauſe<note n="n" place="margin">Doc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or <hi>Drake</hi> in his ſixteen Anti-queries, in the Preface and p. 6.</note> Doctor <hi>Drake</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
aſſerts, <hi>That not onely a ſcandalous Christian, but a very Heathen may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
at the Lords Supper, and heare the prayers and exhortations, ſee the Elements
conſecrated, and all the Sacramentall actions, and that with a great deale of profit, if
the Lord pleaſe to ſanctifie theſe things to him, yet neither of them may be admitted
to partake of the Ordinance it ſelfe, or outward Elements,</hi> though of all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comitants
and actions of it; a prettty novell, <hi>Popiſh whimſey,</hi> contrary to
<hi>Antiquity,</hi> and the practice <hi>of the pureſt times, who admitted none to be preſent at
the Sacrament but ſuch as did actually receive it,</hi> as <hi>Thomas Beacon</hi> proves at large
in his <hi>Catechiſme,</hi> vol. 1. f. 462. Finally, it is aſſerted by all our<note n="o" place="margin">Maſter <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therfards</hi> Due right of Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteries, c. 9. ſect. 9. &amp;c. 4. ſect. 5. p. 186.</note> Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites,
That <hi>the true Saints of God endued with ſaving faith, may fall into ſcandalous<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
ſinnes as well as unregenerate perſons; for which they may be juſtly ſuſpended from the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115480:14"/>
Lords Supper, though admitted to other Ordinances:</hi> Now ſuch cannot be ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended
from the Lords Supper, if they deſire to receive it, as it is a Seale
of Grace, becauſe they have a true intereſt in the Covenant of Grace, and
by reaſon of their frailty and lapſe into ſinne, have more need of this
confirming, ſealing Ordinance to ſtrengthen, encreaſe their graces, and
fortifie them the more againſt all future relapſes after their fals, then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore:
Wherefore this Objection extends not unto ſuch.</p>
               <p>To cloſe up my Anſwer to this grand Objection; admit the Sacraments
to be ſuch Seales of the Covenant of Grace, as Divines now make them, I
would then be reſolved by them; Firſt, Whether the Covenant of Grace
and promiſes of ſalvation, which God hath ratified<note n="a" place="margin">Heb. 6. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, to 20.</note> 
                  <hi>with an Oath,</hi> and by
<hi>the death and paſſion of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">2 Cor. 1. 19, 23.</note> 
                  <hi>in whom all the promiſes of God are Yea, and in
him Amen, to the praiſe and glory of God,</hi> be compleat, firme, valid in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
without theſe Seales annexed to them; or meerly void and null in
Law, as Kings, or mens Deeds and Charters are without a Seale to ratifie
them? If firme, valid, compleat without them; then how are they ſeales
and ratifications of the Covenant of Grace, as ſeales are of royall Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters?
If incompleat, infirme, invalid; that were extreamly derogatory
to the Covenant, promiſes themſelves, to the Oath, the truth of God, the
death of Chriſt, yea directly contrary to Gen. 17. 7, 8. Exod. 6. 4, 5. Levit.
26. 42. 1 Sam. 16. 15, 16, 17, 18. 2 Chron. 6. 14. Nehem. 1. 5. chap. 9.
32. Pſal. 89. 28, 29, 34. Pſal. 105. 10. Pſal. 111. 5, 7, 8, 9. Iſa. 54. 7. to
11. Iſa. 55. 3. Iſa. 61. 8. Jer. 31. 31. to 38. chap. 33. 20, 21. chap. 50. 5.
Ezek. 37. 26, 27. Heb. 6. 17, 18. chap. 13. 20. Therefore they are not
properly ſeales. Secondly, Whether theſe Seales are inſeparably annexed
to the Covenant and promiſes of Grace in the Old or New Teſtament, as
parts or parcels of them, as ſeales are annexed to Charter? If yea, then ſhew
us to what Covenants and promiſes, and in, and by what Texts they are
thus inſeperably annexed; and how any can be ſaved or made partakers of
the benefit of the Covenant and promiſes of Grace, who doe not actually
receive theſe Seales of Grace; when as your ſelves, with all<note n="c" place="margin">Harmony of Confeſſions, ſect. 13. 14.</note> orthodox Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines
muſt grant; that many who were never baptized, and infinite who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
received the Lords Supper, are and may be ſaved, and are made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers
of the Covenant, the promiſes of Grace, without receiving or enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
theſe Seales of Grace. If no, then how can theſe be tearmed, <hi>Seales
of the Covenant and promiſes of Grace,</hi> which are not inſeparably affixed to
them, as ſeales are to Charters? ſince many receive the Covenant and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes
of Grace without theſe Seales, and others receive theſe Seales with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
the Covenant or promiſes, the benefit whereof they never enjoy.
Thirdly, By what reaſon, or upon what ſolid grounds they can deny the
Seales of the Covenant and promiſes to thoſe very ſcandalous or ignorant
Chriſtians once a moneh, a quarter, a yeer, to whom they every day or
week, without any ſcruple, preach, tender, hold forth the very Covenant
and promiſes of Grace, to which they ſay theſe Seales are annexed? Can
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115480:15"/>
men have an intereſt in any Covenant, Deed, Charter made, tendred <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
them, and yet have no right nor intereſt in the Seals annexed to them? an
intereſt in a Coporation Patent, or Charter of pardon, and yet no right
nor intereſt in the ſeales thereto affixed? This certainly is a monſter, a
ſoleciſme in Law, why not them in Divinity too, eſpecially in this point,
wherein Divines turne Lawyers, and allude to Law aſſurances? If then
they will grant the Lords Supper to be a Seale of the Covenant and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes
of Grace, they muſt either deliver and give this Seale to all thoſe vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
Church-members, to whom they daily preach and tender the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
and promiſes of Grace, which is the maine (the Seale being but the
<note n="c" place="margin">Accoſſorium ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>quitor prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipale.</note> 
                  <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ceſſary, which neceſſarily followes the principle,</hi> as Lawyers determine) or elſe
deny to preach or tender the Covenant and promiſes to thoſe to whom
they deny the ſeal and ſo by conſequence muſt exclude all ignorant, at leſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
ſcandalous Chriſtians from hearing the Word read or preached, as
well as ſuſpend them from the Lords Supper; which by their own aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
is but a Seale, and appendant to the Covenant and Promiſes of
Grace, and muſt not be divided from them.</p>
               <p>Fourthly it is objected,<note place="margin">Objection 4.</note>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">Antiquaeries, Maſter <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therfords</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine right of Church-go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, p. 523, &amp;c. <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
                  </note> That <hi>the Lords Supper is no converting Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,
to conferre and bege<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>grace where it is wanting, but onely to confirme it,
where it is already wrought;</hi> therefore ſcandalous perſons ought to be ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended
from the Lords Supper, though admitted to the preaching of the
Word.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, Firſt, that I have ſufficiently re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ted this Objection<note n="q" place="margin">See a Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ation of four ſerious Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, pag. 40. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>elſwhere,</hi>
and proved the the Lords Supper to be a converting Ordinance to beget
grace, as well as a confirming to encreaſe it, by reaſons not yet anſwered;
and (as I conceive) unanſwerable, which I ſhall not here repeat; yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<note n="r" place="margin">Sixteen An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquaeries, the Preface, p. 1. &amp; 6.</note> Doctor <hi>Drake</hi> and others (out of their ignorance or wilfulneſſe)
ſtile this A NEW PARADOX AND MISTAKE OF MASTER
PRINNES, as if I were the firſt broacher of this truth; I ſhall onely
adde ſomething <hi>de novo</hi> for refutation of their miſtake.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt, it is moſt apparent, that in the Primitive Church the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
was</hi> administred to Christians every day, <hi>at l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſt</hi> every Lords day, <hi>and that</hi>
the Ministers and Fathers in thoſe times preſſed all their Auditors to a frequent parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation
of this heavenly Banquet; <hi>upon this very ground, that</hi> thoſe who alwayes
ſinne, might alwayes receive the medicine of this heavenly Sacrament againſt their
ſins, and daily receive it, that they might be daily healed by it; <hi>and</hi> becauſe nothing was
more effectuall to an holy and unblamable life, then the frequent participation of it:
<hi>This is irrefragably proved by</hi> Justin Martyr, <hi>Apolog.</hi> 2. Ignatius, <hi>Epiſt.
ad Epheſianos;</hi> Tertullian, <hi>Apologia;</hi> Ambroſe, <hi>de Sacramentis, l. 4. c. 6. l.</hi> 5.
<hi>c.</hi> 4. Augustine, <hi>Epiſt. 108. ad Januarium Ep. de Eccleſiaſt. Dogm. c. 53. &amp; in
ſoan. 6. Tract.</hi> Hierom <hi>ad Lucinium Epiſt.</hi> Chryſostom <hi>Orat. de B. Philogonio
&amp; Hom. 6. ad Pop. Antioch.</hi> Cyprian <hi>de Caena Domini:</hi> Gratian <hi>de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrat.
Diſt.</hi> 2. Ivo Carnotenſis <hi>Decret. pars 2. c. 24. to 35. Durandus Rat.
Diu. Offic. l. 4. with</hi>
                  <note n="s" place="margin">Harmony of Confeſſions, ſect. 14.</note> ſundry others, and largly manifeſted by Thomas Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115480:15"/>
                  <hi>in his Cat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>chiſme, vol. 1. f. 463. When this pious cuſtome began to be
diſcontinued, we find divers Decrees &amp; Canons made to enforce them to a
frequent reception of this heavenly repaſt;</hi>
                  <note n="s" place="margin">Platina in vita ejus, and <hi>The Becons</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>techiſme, fol. 463.</note> Anacletus <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Rome <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed,
That</hi> Christians ſhould receive the Euchariſt every day, and that thoſe who
would not thus communicate, ſhould be excommunicated: <hi>But ſome of his Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors
finding people more backwards to this holy Ordinance then former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
condiſcending to their humours in ſome ſort, enjoyned by their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees,</hi>
That ALL perſons ſhould, if not more frequently, yet at leastwiſe thrice every
yeer receive the Lords Supper; <hi>to wit,</hi> at Easter, Pentecoſt, the Nativity of Chriſt,
and every Lords day in Lent; <hi>witneſſe the Decrees of Pope</hi> Fabian <hi>&amp;</hi> Silverius,
<hi>recorded by</hi>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">De Conſect. Diſt. 2.</note> Gratian,<note n="v" place="margin">Decretalium pars 2. c 27, 29,</note> Iv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Carnotenſis; <hi>and</hi>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">Ivo Carno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſis, Decret. pars 2 c 28. Lutheri Care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſmus major</note> 
                  <hi>Saint</hi> Hilary <hi>decreed,</hi> That if a
mans ſinnes were not ſo great as that he were to be excommunicated, <hi>non debet a
medicina corporis Domini ſeperari,</hi> he ought not to be ſequestred from the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine
of the Lords Body; <hi>unde timendum eſt ne DIU abſtractus a Chriſti
corpore, alienus remaneat à ſalute; nam manifeſtum eſt vivere, qui corpu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
attingunt Chriſti, &amp;c. Beſides theſe, the</hi>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">Surjus Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. Tom. 1. p. 712. Gratian de Conſecr. Diſt. 2. Ivo Decret. pars 2. c 33.</note> Councill <hi>of</hi> Agatha <hi>about the</hi> 440.
<hi>yeer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> after Chriſt, decreed, That</hi> ſecular men who rece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d not the Lords Supper in
Christs Nativity, Easter and Pentecoſt, ſhould not be reputed Catholicks, nor numbred
among Catholicks; <hi>which is ſeconded by ſundry other forraigne Councils,
as</hi>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">Bochellus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, Eccleſ. Gal. l. 2 Tit. 7. c 5. l 3. Tit. 1, c 20, 23, 24, 93, 95, 103, 104, 105, 106, 138.</note> Synod. Turon, 3. <hi>ſub. Kar. Magno.</hi> Concil. Burdig, 1582. Concil. Bitur,
1584. Aquenſ. 1585. Theodulphus Aurelian, <hi>Epiſt. An.</hi> 835. Synod. Carnot,
1526. Concil. Rhomenſe, 1583. <hi>&amp; Synod. Paris 1557. Yea, our owne anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
Britiſh Councils, as</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Spelmanni Concil. Tom. 1. p 519, 548, 615, 616.</note> Concil. Aenhamenſe Generale, <hi>An. 1009. the</hi> Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>icall
Lawes <hi>of King</hi> Knute, <hi>An. 1032. with other ancient chapters, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ribe,
that</hi> every Pariſhioner ſhould receive the Sacrament at leaſt thrice every yeer:
and <hi>the Bubrick in the old Common-Prayer Book after the Communion,
w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>h the 21 Canon, made Anno</hi> 1505<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>enjoin, That EVERY PARISHI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ONER</hi>
ſhall receive the Lords Supper <hi>at leſt</hi> three times every yeer, of which Laster
to be one; And that in Cathedrall and Collegiall Churches, where be many Priests and
Deacons, they ſhall all receive the Communion with the Minister <hi>EVERY SUN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DAY
AT THE LEAST,</hi> except they have a reaſonable cauſe to the con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rary:
<hi>Yea, our learned</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">In his Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme, vol. 1. f 461, 463.</note> Beacon <hi>reckons up this as a great abuſe, and POPISH
INNOVATION; that</hi> whereas: the Lord Chriſt Jeſus would have the holy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion
of his bleſſed. Body and precious Blood to be oft times received of the: faithfull for
a remembrance of his death and paſſion, and for the worthy, earneſt, diligent conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of this inestimable benefit which we have obtained of God the Father, through the
Sonne his paſſion and death: the custome of the Popes Church is, that the people receive
the Sacrament uſually but once in the yeer, that is to ſay, at Eaſter; by<note n="g" place="margin">See <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> p. 542. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 550. to like pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</note> which meanes
the commandement of Chriſt is broken, the Sacrament is neglected, the death of Chriſt
not ſo earneſtly remembred, the people become unthankefull, diſſolution of life breaketh
in, vice increaſeth, vertue decreaſeth; <hi>which he condemnes as contrary both
the Scripture and Antiquity; informing us, That</hi> among the Greeks, even at
this day, if any man abſent himſelfe from the Lords Table by the ſpace of fourteen dayes
(except be can render a reaſonable cauſe of his abſence) he is excommunicate, and put
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115480:16"/>
from the company of the faithfull; and that in all thoſe mighty, large, populous King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes
under that moſt puiſſant King <hi>Prceious John,</hi> the holy communion of the Body
and Blood of the Lord hath from the beginning been <hi>DAILY ADMINISTRED
TO THE PEOPLE,</hi> and yet is at this preſent day, as Hiſtories make mention:
<hi>All which, as it juſtly refutes and cenſures the late unwarrantable, that I
ſay not impious, popiſh, tyrannicall practice of ſundry of our Miniſters,
who (I know not out of what new whimſeys &amp; pretended ſcruples of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience)
contrary to Antiquity, Scripture, Law, the conſtant practice of
the Church in all Ages, refuſe to adminiſter the Sacrament to their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhoners
for whole yeers together or more, denying this heavenly Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
of Chriſt, as well to the religious among them who deſire it, as to
the ignorant, ſcandalous, prophane; proſtituting this Inſtitution of Chriſt
himſelfe to their owne ambitious deſignes, to encroach a juriſdiction over
it and their peoples conſciences by this irreligious ſtratagem, no wayes
juſtifiable before God or men; ſo it yeelds me an unanſwerable argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
to prove theſe two concluſions, neceſſarily ſlowing from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, that the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> by the judgement of Antiquity and the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice
of the Church in all Ages, belongs to all viſible members of the viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
Church, able to examine themſelves, not actually excommunicated,
though they be not truly regenerated; becauſe all of them are thus equally
enjoyned frequently to receive it, as well as to heare the Word.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that the Lords Supper by the reſolution of all theſe Fathers,
Authors, and the Chriſtian Church in all Ages, is a <hi>converting, regenerating,
as well as a confirming or ſealing Ordinance;</hi> for ſince every pariſhoner and
member of each Congregation being of yeers of diſcretion, was thus
<hi>exhorted, obliged to receive it at leaſt three times every yeer, under paine of excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication
and not being reputed a chriſtian;</hi> the greateſt part of whom, as the
Scripture and experience informe us, were unregenerate perſons, not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly
converted, and void of ſaving faith; the eating of this heavenly
Banquet could not be preſcribed unto ſuch, as a bare ſealing or confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Ordinance of ſaving grace already received, much leſſe as a meanes of
their condemnation or aggravation of their ſinnes; but onely as an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of their inward converſion and regeneration, to beget ſaving faith
and ſpirituall life within their ſoules, and unite them unto Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hence the</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Bochellus de cret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Eccleſ. Gal. l 3. Tit. 1. c 2. p 356.</note> 
                  <hi>Synod of</hi> Lingon <hi>An. 1404. defines thus;</hi> Sacramentum Sanctae E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſtiae
eſt excellentiſſimum Sacramentum, pro eo quod non ſolum <hi>IN EO GRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIA
CONFERTUR</hi> &amp; ſanctificat, ſeu ſanctitatem cauſat, ſicut alia Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta;
ſed etiam quia continet in ſe actorem totius gratiae &amp; ſanctificationis, Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuin
noſtrum Jeſum Chriſtum. <hi>Hence the Synod of</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Bochellus de eret. Eccleſ. Gal. l 2. Tit. 1. c 34 p 152, 153.</note> Sennes, <hi>An. 1521. refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
ſuch who</hi> deny the power of conferring grace to the Sacraments, <hi>not onely
proves,</hi> Baptiſmi Sacramentum ſua virtute conferre Gratiam, <hi>ſtiling it,</hi> Lava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crum
regenerationis quo denuo naſtimur; <hi>but likewiſe reſolves thus of the Lords
Supper;</hi> Quis autem <hi>VIVIFIC UM</hi> neget Euchariſtiae Sacramentum, quod tam
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115480:16"/>
apertis Scripturae testimoniis comprobatur? Calix enim benedictionis cui benedicimus,
nonne communio ſanguinis Christi eſt? &amp; panis quem frangimus, nonne participatio corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris
Domini eſt? &amp;c. Quibus luce clarius constet, hoc ſacroſanctam Eucharistiae Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum
non ſolnm <hi>GRATIAM CONFERRE,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Which thus interpreted and
ſeconded by the Synod of</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Bochel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus ibid. c. 32. p. 148</note> Paris, <hi>Anno 1557. may paſſe for orthodox truth;</hi>
Sacramentum juxta nominis etymologiam, id ſignificat <hi>QUO QUID SACRATUR.</hi>
Sacramentum itaque ex more Catholicae Eccleſiae, dicitur ſacrae rei ſignum externum &amp;
ſenſibile, efficaci ſignificatione, inſinuans internam &amp; inviſibilem gratiam Dei, aut effectum
gratuitum ex divina institutione ad ſalutem mortalium destinatum: Sacramenta duabus
potiſſimum de cauſis a Deo eſſe instituta videntur. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na eſt, ut ſint inviſibilis ſanctificatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis
inſignia &amp; externa ſigna Christiani, ini, illius quae magnae Congregationis, quae eſt Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia,
ſigilla, ne Domini familia, aliarum gentium admixtione, fiat incerta: <hi>Altera</hi> cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa
eſt, ut Sacramenta ipſa non tantum ſignificent, <hi>ſed etiam ſanctificent &amp; conferant
inviſibilem Dei Gratiam;</hi> non propria aliqua rerum externorum vi, aut merito mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtri,
ſed Domini ſecretius operantis quod instituit. Itaque etſi decet bonum eſſe Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum
ministrum, tamen malus etiam poteſt utiliter diſpenſare. Quum dicimus Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum
cauſam eſſe justificationis nostrae, intellegimus non principalem ſed instrumentalem, &amp;
ſine qua res fieri non ſolet, quamvis ſine ea fieni poſſit; nec enim virtus Domini &amp; poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia
alligata eſt Sacramentis. Eccleſiae Sacramenta, ſunt a Christo in morborum animi re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medium
&amp; curationem instituta; quorum haec vis eſt, ut <hi>ſacros ſanctoſque faciant,</hi> qui
ea digne ſuſcipitunt; quando non ſigna quidem ſolum ſunt gratiae, <hi>ſed ipſus cauſa;</hi> his non
modo ſignando ſed &amp; efficiendo <hi>ſanctitatem Chriſtus</hi> nobis conferre voluit. <hi>Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta</hi>
igitur non tantummodo ſigna ſunt quae infuſam gratiam contegant &amp; occultent, <hi>ſed quae
efficiant, &amp; reipſa preſtant &amp; cujus notae ſunt &amp; ſigna;</hi> eſt autem Sacramentum di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinae
gratiae ſignum &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igura, <hi>acinſtrumentalis cauſa, efficiens inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taliter quod</hi>
ſenſibiliter figurat. <hi>Henc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Bochel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus ibid. c. 5. p. 142.</note> 
                  <hi>the Councill of</hi> Burdeaux <hi>Anno 1582. defines the like
in theſe termes:</hi> Cum Eccleſia nihil habet precioſius, nihil ad aeternam ſalutem conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quendam
magis neceſſarium, quàm â Christo instituta Sacramenta, quibus omnis juſtitia
vel <hi>INCIPIATUR,</hi> vel caepta augeatur, vel amiſſa reparatur, ac Domini Dei gratia,
quam ipſa Sacramenta, ſeu vaſa quaedam divina continent, eamque ritè ſuſcipientibus <hi>CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FERUNT,</hi>
nobis abunde communicetur, paſtores omni ſtudio &amp; diligentia commiſſum ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi
Chriſtianum populum exhortare debent ad frequentem Auguſtiſſimi Euchariſtiae Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti
uſum: <hi>And</hi> Concilium<note n="g" place="margin">Bochel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus ibid. c<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. p. 14<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Bitur, <hi>Anno 1584. concludes thus;</hi> Cum per primum
parentem violata eſt originalis juſtitia in qua creatus fuerat, &amp; peccato ſuo omnes p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s
infecit, &amp;c. Providus Deus ſingulls morbis ſingula adhibuit remedia; Sacramenta ſcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet,
quibus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> peccata remittuntur; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ominis vita reg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>vr, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ides augetur, &amp; totius Eccleſiae
politia continetur ac conſervatur: <hi>NAM SPIRITUALEM HOMINI VITAM
CONFERUNT BAPTISMUS, EUCHARISTIA, &amp;c. By all which it is
apparent that the Lords Supper and Baptiſme are converting as well as confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
Ordinances, and were ſo reputed in moſt</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">See <hi>Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 4. ſent. qu. 1 &amp; <hi>Aretius</hi> Problem. Theol. loc 76.</note> 
                  <hi>former Ages till this preſent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, it is undeniable that <hi>Juſtin Martyr, Dyoniſius Arcopagita, Athanaſius,
Baſil, Ambroſe, Cyprian, Auguſtine, Bernard</hi> and other Ancients from Gal. 3. 17.
Rom. 6. 3. Eph. 5. 26. Tit. 3. 5. 1 Pet. 5. 31. ſtile Baptiſme, <hi>the Sacrament of
divine Generation, the laver of Regeneration, A New Birth, the Regeneration of the ſoul,
the Mother of our Adoption, &amp;c.</hi> and call Baptizing, <hi>giving Gods Grace;</hi> denying it,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115480:17"/>
                  <hi>denying Gods Grace,</hi> as Maſter<note n="h" place="margin">Defence of Infant. Baptiſme par. 1. &amp;<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Marſhall</hi> proves at large, and many of them hold
<hi>That thoſe who dyed without Baptiſme could not be ſaved;</hi> Yea, moſt<note n="i" place="margin">In 4 ſent Diſt. 1. 4. &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Treatiſes of baptiſm</note> 
                  <hi>Papiſts</hi> hold, and
many Proteſtants aſſert, that Baptiſme is not onely a badge, but inſtrumentall
meanes of our regeneration and firſt converſion unto God; and if this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
be a converting as well as a ſealing Ordinance, then the Lords Supper
by like reaſon muſt be ſo too.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, all Popiſh <hi>Schoolmen, Writers, Councils</hi> unanimouſly aſſert, <hi>That Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments</hi>
(eſpecially Baptiſme and the Lords Supper) <hi>not only confirm, but confer and
beget grace, even the very firſt grace of converſion and juſtification, and that either in a
phyſicall way</hi> ex opere operato (as moſt of them affirme) <hi>or as</hi>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">Maſter <hi>Ruther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>urds</hi> Due right of Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, c. 4. ſect. 5. p. 212.</note> 
                  <hi>morall cauſes</hi> (as
others teach) and <hi>that they are the veſſels in and by which the merits of Chriſt are
conveyed to, and conferred on us:</hi> Witneſſe <hi>Paſcatius Rathbertus,</hi> de Corpore &amp; San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine
Domini, c. 3. <hi>Aquinas, Durandus, Occam, Bonaventura, Scotus, Media Villa,
Brulifer, Egidus Romanus, Joan</hi> de Carthagena, <hi>Hadrianus Florentius, Dom. à Soto,
Holcot, Gabriel Biel, Aliacenſis,</hi> and other Schoolmen, in lib. 4. Sent. Diſt. 1.
<hi>Alenſis,</hi> Summa Theologiae, pars 4. qu. 5. mem. 3. Art. 5. <hi>Aquinas</hi> p. 3. q. 6. 2.
&amp; 63. Art. 6. <hi>Greg. de Valentia,</hi> in 3. part. Thomae Diſp. 3. qu. 3. &amp; de Offic.
Sacr. c. 2. <hi>Vaſquez.</hi> in 3. Thomae, Tom. 2. Diſp. 132. c. 4. <hi>Tannerus</hi> in Thom.
Tom. 4. Diſp. 3. qu. 3. dub. 5. <hi>Gamachaeus</hi> in 3. part Thom. qu. 62. c. 5. <hi>Sum.
Angelica.</hi> Tit. Sacram. <hi>Victor</hi> l. 6. De Sacramentis, parte 9. cap. 2. <hi>Henricus</hi>
quod l. 4. qu. 37. <hi>Gabriel Biel</hi> Super Can. Miſſae, Lect. 85, 86. <hi>Petrus Binsfiel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius,</hi>
Enchirid. Theologiae pars 1. c. 2. 6. <hi>Joan de Lugo</hi> de Sacram. Diſp. 4. ſect.
4, 5. <hi>Bechanus</hi> Theolog. Scholaſt. pars 4. Tract de Sacram. qu. 7. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> De
Sacram. l. 2. c. 1. to 6. &amp; 11. the <hi>Councill of Trent</hi> Seſſ. 7. Can. 5, 6, 7, 8. de Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentis,
with ſundry others. Therefore this is no new opinion invented
by me.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, though<note n="l" place="margin">See Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſect. 12, 13, 14 <hi>Calvin,</hi> Inſtit. l. 4. c. 13, 14, 15. <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> in Rom. 4. <hi>Aretius</hi> Problem. Theol. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o cus 76, 77 <hi>Willets</hi> Sy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nopſis Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmipi cent 2. Err. 97. 98. <hi>Ameſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Bellar. Enerva <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s</hi> Tom. 3. c. 5.</note> Proteſtant Writers unanimouſly and juſtly oppoſe the
Papiſts in this, That <hi>the Sacraments by a phiſicall vertue,</hi> or ex opere operato, <hi>confer
grace,</hi> yet they generally grant, that <hi>they are the meanes, Organs, or inſtrumentall
cauſes of conferring, confirming grace, through the concurrence of Gods Spirit working in
and by them, as well as by the Word, where they are worthily received by faith;</hi> but that
they originally beget ſaving grace, faith and ſpirituall life in ſuch in whom
they were formerly wanting, is denied by ſome of them, yet affirmed by others:
Indeed the Author of the <hi>Confeſſion of</hi>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, ſect. 12. p. 279, 280, 281. l. 4. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4.</note> 
                  <hi>Bohemia,</hi>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">Decad. 5. Serm. 7</note> 
                  <hi>Calvin,</hi>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">Tract<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Theol<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> p. 350, 357.</note> 
                  <hi>Bullinger, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſinus,</hi>
ſeem to deny <hi>the Sacraments to be converting Ordinances, but confirming onely:</hi> Yet
others (eſpecially the Lutherans) hold the contrary. <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary
on Rom. 4. writes, That <hi>one chiefe end of the Sacraments is, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t accendant
in nobis fidem, Dei;</hi> and that <hi>they doe</hi> CONFERRE GRATIAM in that ſenſe
as <hi>Paul</hi> cals the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> the power of God unto ſalvation; <hi>quod ſanè nihil aliud
eſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> quàm vim &amp; potentiam Dei qua peccata remittit,</hi> GRATIAM LARGITUR,
<hi>&amp; denique ſervat his inſtrumentis &amp; mediis uti</hi> ad ſalutem noſtram: <hi>Ad quod efficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum
quemadmodum utitur verbo Evangelii, &amp; praedicatione Sacrarum Literarum, ita
etiam adhibet</hi> Sacramenta: <hi>Per utraque enim praedicatur nobis liberalis Dei prom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſio.</hi>
Therefore in his opinion the Word and Sacraments are both alike converting
Ordinances.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:115480:17"/>
                  <hi>Martin Luther</hi> in his<note n="h" place="margin">In concordia Lutherana<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> p. 378.</note> 
                  <hi>leſſer Catechiſme</hi> demanding this queſtion. <hi>What doth it
profit us to eat and drink the Lords Supper?</hi> returnes this anſwer; <hi>Id indicant no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>c verba,</hi> pro vobis dat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> effunditur in remiſſionem peccutorum: <hi>Nem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe,
qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d nobis per verba illa in Sacramento,</hi> REMISSIO PECCATORUM
VITA, JUSTITIA ET SALVS DONENTUR, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi enim remiſſio
peccatorum eſt, ibi eſt &amp; vita &amp; ſalus:</hi> Therefore he<note n="a" place="margin">So doe his followers; ſee <hi>Brochman,</hi> lyſt. Theol. To n. 3. de Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cram. c. 21. qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 1. &amp; 6.</note> deemed it a regenerating
and converting, as well as a confirming Ordinance: <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>etius,</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem.
Theolog. Locus 77. Sect. 7. determines thus; <hi>Deo permittend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> eſt libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra
agendi facultas; aliàs regenerat an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>è, aliàs poſt, aliàs</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">Plane nemo dubita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e debet quod in alvo Baptiſmi, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſquam In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fans a fonte ſurgat, ſpiritu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſanctus in ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam renaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centis in fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur, &amp;c. <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catius Rathher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> de corporo &amp; ſanguine Domini, c. 3.</note> IN BAPTISMO; <hi>ſio
aliàs antè Coenam, aliàs poſt, aliàs</hi> IN ILLA CONVERTIT AD VERAM
P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>NITENTIAM; <hi>ſed quotquot regenerat &amp; convertit ad veram paenitentiam
illa bona in eis obſignat uſu Sacramentorum:</hi> Hence <hi>Augustine</hi> in Pſal. 73. torms
them, <hi>Sacramenta</hi> DANTIA SALUTEM: And <hi>Hilary</hi> l. 8. de Trinitate,
writes thus of the Sacramentall Elements, thus accompanied with the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit;
<hi>Haec accepta atque exhausta</hi> EFFICIUNT, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s nos in Christo &amp; Christus
in nobis ſit:</hi> Therefore by their reſolutions the <hi>Lords Supper</hi> and <hi>Baptiſme</hi>
are <hi>converting</hi> as well as <hi>confirming</hi> or <hi>Sealing</hi> Ordinances: Yea, <hi>Victor An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochenus</hi>
in cap. 14. Marci, together with <hi>Chryſostome</hi> and<note n="k" place="margin">Summa The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olog. pars 4. qu. 11. Artic. 1. ſect. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Alenſis,</hi> affirme,
That <hi>Chriſt admitted</hi> Judas <hi>to his Supper for this very reaſon, That he might leave
no meanes unattempted to reclaime, convert and reduce him to a ſound<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nind;</hi> which
cleerly proves it to be a converting Ordinance in their judgments.</p>
               <p>The opinion of <hi>Augustine</hi> is notorious, that the Sacraments both of <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme</hi>
and the <hi>Lords Supper</hi> are ſo neceſſary, that <hi>none could be ſaved without them,</hi>
and therefore <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e</hi> and the Church of <hi>Carthage</hi> maintained, That <hi>not only Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme,
but the</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">Epiſt. 23. contra Pelagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anos Hypog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> l. 5. cont. duas Epiſt. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagii ad Bone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facium, lib. 1. c. 22. &amp; l. 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> c. 4. contr. Juli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anum Pelag. l. 1. &amp; 2. Tit. 3. 1 Pet. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Lords Supper alſo ought to be given unto Infants, elſe they could not be
ſaved:</hi> I ſhall quote but one place of his inſtead of many: <hi>De peccatorum
Meritis &amp; Remiſſione, &amp; de Baptiſmo parvulorum,</hi> l. 1. c. 24. <hi>Optimè Punici Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ani
Baptiſmum ipſum nihil aliud</hi> QUAM SALUTEM, <hi>&amp; Sacramentum cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris
Christi, nihil aliud</hi> QUAM VITAM VOCANT; <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde, niſi ex anti
qua, ut existimo, &amp; Apostolica traditione, qua Eccleſiae Christi inſitum tenent, praeter
Baptiſmum &amp; participationem Dominicae menſae, non ſolum ad regnum Dei, ſed nec</hi>
AD SALUTEM ET VITAM AETERNAM <hi>poſſe quenquam
hominum per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>enire? Hoc enim &amp; Scriptura testatur, ſecundum ea quae ſupra dixi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus:
Nam quid aliud tenent, qui Baptiſmum nomine ſalutis appellant, niſi quod di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum
eſt;</hi> Salvos nos fecit per lavachrum regenerationis; Et quod Petrus <hi>ait,</hi>
ſic &amp; vos ſimili forma Baptiſmus ſalvos fecit:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oan. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>id aliud etiam qui Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum
menſae Dominicae</hi> VITAM <hi>vocant, niſi quod dictum eſt;</hi> Ego ſum panis
vitae qui de Coelo deſcendi; &amp; panis quem ego dedero, caro mea eſt pro ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culi
vita: <hi>Et,</hi> Si non manducaveritis carnem filii hominis &amp; ſanguinem bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beritis,
non habebitis vitam in vobis: <hi>ſi ergo ut tot &amp; tanta divina testimonia con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinunt,</hi>
NEC SALUS, NEC VITA AETERNA <hi>ſine Baptiſmo &amp;
cortore &amp; ſanguine Domini cuiquam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>peranda eſt, frustra ſine his promittitur parvulis.</hi>
After which he concludes; <hi>Proindè parvuli ſi</hi> PER SACRAMEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TUM
QUOD AD HOC DIVINITUS INSTITU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TUM
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115480:18"/>
TUM EST, IN CREDENTIUM NUMERUM NON
TRANSEANT, <hi>profectò in his tenetris (peccatorum) rema<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>bant:</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
by his and the Church of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>arthage</hi> reſolution, yea the<note n="l" place="margin">See Capit. Karol. &amp; Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dovici, l. 1. c. 161.</note> Churches judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
from the Apoſtles dayes (it being an <hi>Apostolicall tradition embraced by
the Church,</hi> as he avers) theſe Sacraments are the originall primary meanes
both of converſion, ſpirituall life, and ſalvation, and ſo converting as well
as confirming Ordinances. <hi>Cypriam</hi> de Coena Domini, writes, That the
Lords Supper, <hi>Ad totius hominis vitam ſalutem qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> profic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, ſimul medica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mentum
&amp; holocau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ium ad ſanandas infirmitates, &amp; purgandas miquitates existens<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
a converting Ordinance as well as a confirming. <hi>Cyrill</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi>
De Juſtificatione in Chriſto, lib. 3. affirmes, That <hi>Death fed upon men on earth
untill the institution of the Lords Supper, wherein we eat the living Bread from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven;
from which time death hath ceaſed, and the inhabitants of the holy City, the
Church, are perfected unto ſanctification by that living bread:</hi> Therefore in his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
it is a means of our ſpirituall life and ſanctification, and ſo a conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
Ordinance: The ſayings of the Fathers to this purpoſe are almoſt
infinite; I ſhall therefore pretermit them, challenging my Oppoſites to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
any ſolid Antiquity to the contrary, to prove them not converting
as well as corroborating inſtitutions.</p>
               <p>Neither is this Doctrine a ſtranger in our owne Church; for Biſhop
<hi>Jewell</hi> in his Defence of the Apology of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> part 3. ch.
15. Diviſ. 2. p. 349. determines thus: <hi>But</hi> TO BREED AND
ENCREASE FAITH IN US, <hi>there are more wayes then can be
reckoned: Some men are moved onely by the hearing of Gods Word; ſome others by the
beholding and weighing of Gods Miracles: Justinus</hi> the Martyr <hi>was firſt allured to
the faith by the cruelty of the Tyrants, and by the constancy and patience of the Saints,
&amp;c.</hi> Among OTHER CAUSES, THE SACRAMENTS
SERVE SPECIALLY TO DIRECT AND TO AYD
OUR FAITH; <hi>For they are, as</hi> Saint Auguſtine calleth them, Verba
viſibilia, <hi>viſible words and Seales, and testimonies of the Goſpell, &amp;c.</hi> Our learned
<hi>Thomas Beacon</hi> in his Catechiſme, f. 425, 426. thus defines a Sacrament; <hi>A
Sacrament is an holy Action and exerciſe of Chriſts Church IN which the redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
and partaking of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> IS GIVEN TO US <hi>through
the Word, and the Signes</hi> INSTITUTED FOR THIS PUR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>POSE
OF GOD.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>After which he propounds this pertinent Queſtion:</hi> What need have
we of Sacraments, ſeeing we have the holy Ghoſt and the ſacred Scriptures of God to
lead us unto all neceſſary truth, which can abundantly informe us of the grace, favour,
mercy and good will of God towards us? <hi>Which he anſwers thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Chriſt the wiſdome of the Father, knowing our groſſeneſſe and dulneſſe in understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
matters that belong unto our ſalvation, wiſhing our health and commodity, and
minding to remedy and help this our great infirmity, and to bring us unto ſome know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
of Gods mysteries, that we may be ſaved, hath not onely given us his holy ſpirit to
informe, instruct and teach our inward man, but to make us perfect both in body and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115480:18"/>
ſoule; he hath alſo given his Word to instruct our eares, and his Sacraments to ſerve
our eyes: For whatſoever the holy Ghoſt ſaith inwardly unto us, the very ſame doth
the Word of God unto our eares<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the Sacraments to ſerve our eyes, preach, declare
and ſet forth outwardly,<note place="margin">Note.</note> that we may be taught both corporally and ſpiritually. Againe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
who knoweth not that things ſeen with eyes are more ſurely fixed in the minds of men,
then thoſe things which are onely heard? And therefore a Sacrament may right well be
called a viſible word: For whatſoever the word is to the eare, the very ſame thing is
the Sacrament to the eye: The Word of God ſaith to mine care, the Body of Chriſt was
broken for thee; the very ſame thing doth the Sacrament preach to mine eye, while in
the holy action of the Lords Supper, I ſee the bread broken and the wine ſhed: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
Chriſt the Lord to informe and instruct our outward ſenſes, ordained theſe outward
ſignes and Sacraments, that by the conſideration and beholding of them, the thing
might the more eaſily ſlide into our minds, which hath been inculked and beaten in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
our ears through the voice of the Preaher: If we had been without bodies, Chriſt
would have given unto us thoſe ſpirituall gifts nakedly and ſimply, which are given to
the faithfull in the deliverance of the Sacraments; but foraſmuch as we have bodies
joyned to our ſoules, therefore in ſenſible things he doth communicate unto us the
gifts of grace; and this hath been the property of God not onely in the New, but alſo in
the old Teſtament.</p>
               <p>If then the Sacraments be <hi>but viſible words,</hi> which <hi>preach the ſelf-ſame
things</hi> (yet in a more lively and ſenſible manner) <hi>to our eyes, as the Word
preached doth unto our eares,</hi> as this Author, with all<note n="m" place="margin">Calvin, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanchton, Peter Martyr, Zer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius, Aretius, <hi>and others.</hi>
                  </note> Orthodox Divines,
and<note n="n" place="margin">Due right of Presbyteries, c. 4. ſect. 5. p. 121.</note> Maſter <hi>Rutherfurd</hi> himſelfe, unanimouſly accord; it muſt needs fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low,
that the Sacraments (eſpecially the Lords Supper) moſt lively repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting
Chriſts paſſion to us, muſt be a converting Ordinance, as well as
the Word read or preached: Upon which grou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, <hi>the Ancient Catholick Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi>
(as our owne<note n="o" place="margin">Concerning the Sacrament part 1. p. 189 190.</note> 
                  <hi>Homilies</hi> reſolve) ſtiled the <hi>Lords Supper; A comfortable
medicine of the ſoule, the ſalve of immortality, and ſoveraigne preſervation againſt
death, the Pledge of eternall Health, the defence of faith, the food of immortality, the
be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lthfull grace, and the conſervatory to everlasting life;</hi> therefore they deemed
it a converting as well as con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>irming Ordinance. Maſter <hi>Richard Ward</hi> in
his Commentary upon Matthew, pag. 399. in the written Copy, writes,
Sacraments <hi>doe not conferre Grace upon all, nor by a phyſicall power give grace unto
any; but ſometimes</hi> GOD IN AND BY THE SACRAMENTS
CONVEYES GRACE INTO HIS ELECT CHIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DREN,
<hi>and ſometimes by the Sacraments confirmes grace which he hath formerly
conferred.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not to multiply Authorities in ſo cleer a caſe, the very <hi>Directory</hi> it ſelfe
(compoſed by the <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> and ratified by <hi>both Houſes of Parliament</hi>) pag.
25. enumerates the Word and Sacraments among the ſpeciall meanes of
Grace and ſalvation in theſe words; <hi>To give thanks to God for all his benefits,
and eſpecially for<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> ALL MEANES OF GRACE, THE WORD
AND SACRAMENTS<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>And for this Sacrament in particular, by which
Chriſt and all his benefits are applied and ſealed up unto us;</hi> making them both
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115480:19"/>
equally in the ſelfe ſame manner meanes of grace, and coupling them both
together in the ſelfe ſame predication; therefore if the Word be a meanes
of begetting grace where it was wanting, and of obtaining ſalvation, the
Sacraments muſt be ſo too. In fine,<note n="p" place="margin">Due right of Presbyteries, c. 4. ſect. 5. p. 217.</note> Maſter <hi>Rutherfurd</hi> himſelfe writes
thus: You ſay, Sacraments doe not make a thing that was not, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme
a thing that was before; <hi>while you would ſeem to refute</hi> Papiſts, <hi>who vainly
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>each,</hi> that Sacraments <hi>ex opere operato</hi> doe conferre grace, <hi>yet doe you make
the Sacrament but a naked ſigne, and take part with</hi> Arminians and So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nians,
<hi>whoſe very Arguments in expreſſe words you uſe; for if a Sacrament make not a thing
which was before, and if God give not, and really produce, conferre, exhibit grace, and
a ſtronger meaſure of faith and aſſurance of remiſſion of ſinnes, at the due and right uſe
of the Sacrament, the Sacrament is a naked ſigne, and not an exhibitive Seale; but if
Chriſt give, and in the preſent exhibit as ſurely remiſſion of ſinnes as the Infant is
waſhed with water,</hi> as our Divines and the Palatinate Catechiſme teacheth,
and the Confeſſion thereof and the <hi>Synod</hi> of <hi>Dort</hi> teacheth, then by the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament
of Baptiſme (and ſo by conſequent of the Lords Supper) a <hi>thing
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s made that which it was not before;</hi> therefore by conſequence it is a regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
and converting Ordinance. This he more plainly expreſſeth in<note n="q" place="margin">Maſter <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therfurds</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine right of Church-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, p. 523, 524.</note> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
diſcourſe in thoſe tearmes: Maſter Prynne <hi>might have ſpared his paines
That the Lords Supper is a converting Ordinance, becauſe it applies Chriſt to us;</hi>
WE GRANT IT TO BE A CONVERTING, QUICK<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NING
AND LIVELY APPLICATORY ORDI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NANCE:
<hi>But how? He may know, that whatever Ordinance addeth a new de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree
of Faith,</hi> OF CONVERSION, <hi>of living Application of Chriſt
and the Promiſes,</hi> MUST BE A CONVERTING ORDI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NANCE;
<hi>but it is ſo converting, that it is a confirming Ordinance, and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily
it preſuppoſeth faith and converſion already wrought by the Word; it is not a
firſt converting Ordinance, ſo as is the Word, &amp;c. I ſay not this as if the Church could
give the Supper of the Lord to none but ſuch as are inwardly and really regenerated,
but to ſhew that the Church taketh ſuch as are externally called, to be internally called,
whence they diſpence the Supper to them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In which words, we have a moſt cleer confeſſion, That the <hi>Lords Supper</hi>
is both a converting and quickning Ordinance: But yet this muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trolled
with a diſtinction not found Scripture or Antiquity: <hi>It is ſo a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting
Ordinance, that it is a confirming Ordinance:</hi> I grant it: So is the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
and preaching of the Word<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it converts, yet ſo as it confirmes and edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
us too in our moſt holy faith, yet it is a converting Ordinance.</p>
               <p>Yea, but <hi>it is not the firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>erting Ordinance; it is not the meanes of our firſt
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nverſion from formall profeſſion to inward embracing the Goſpell: For the Word muſt
goe before; and not ſimply the externall Letter of the Word, but the Word firſt beleeved
and received by the efficatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s working of the holy Ghoſt, &amp;c.</hi> This is onely affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
but not ſubſtantially proved by this learned Divine, who takes upon
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to limit God and his Spirit, ſo as to deprive them of their abſolute
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to work and beget grace by the Sacraments when and where they
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115480:19"/>
pleaſe, as well as by the Word; and confines the Spirits firſt inward con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion
of men onely to the Word,<note n="r" place="margin">John 3. 7<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Who breatheth where and in what Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e listeth, the breath of ſpirituall life into our ſoules.</hi> True it is, the Word
preached i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the firſt ordinary and moſt uſuall meanes both of externall and
internall converſion, but yet the Sacraments as well as the Word are very
frequently made the inſtruments, though not of externall converſion of
m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n from Paganiſme to Chrſtianity (not here in queſtion,) yet of carnall
Chriſtians<note n="s" place="margin">See <hi>Ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="5 letters">
                           <desc>•••••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> in Thomam, Tom. 4. Diſp. 3. qu. 3. Du. 50</note> 
                  <hi>firſt inward and reall converſion from ſin &amp; ſatan unto Chriſt, and a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt
effectuall means</hi> both of begetting, encreaſing grace and ſpirituall life in their
ſoules, as I have elſwhere largely evidenced.</p>
               <p>Hence<note n="a" place="margin">Loci <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munes</hi> prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted 153<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> de Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</note> 
                  <hi>Phillip Melanchton</hi> (in a Book Dedicated to our King <hi>Henry</hi> the
VIII) though he deny, that <hi>the Sacraments</hi> ex opere operato <hi>conferre grace
and justification;</hi> yet he expreſly reſolves, that <hi>they were principally inſtituted
to be ſignes of Gods good will towards us, incurring into our eyes, that they may admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh
us TO BELEEVE the promiſe propoſed in the Goſpell: Thus we conjoyne
the Sacrament and promiſe; now as the promiſe is to be received by faith, ſo alſo in
the uſe of the Sacraments faith ought to be added, which may aſſure us, that thoſe true
things ſhall happen which are propounded in the promiſe:</hi> Auguſtine <hi>aptly compares
the Word with the Sacrament, when be ſaith,</hi> The Sacrament is a viſible Word;
that is, <hi>As the Word is a certaine note which is received with the eares, ſo the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
is a ſpectacle or Picture which runs into the eyes: As therefore the Word is a
note ſignifying ſomething of the will of God, and as God is laid hold on in the Word up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
our beliefe, ſo likewiſe is he apprehended in the Sacrament when we beleeve: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
as the Word is an instrument by which the holy Ghoſt is effectuall, as</hi> Paul <hi>ſaith,</hi>
The Goſpell is the power of God to every one that beleeveth: <hi>Alſo,</hi> Faith
is by hearing, &amp;c. <hi>So</hi> BY THE SACRAMENTS <hi>the holy Ghoſt</hi> IS EF<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FECTUALL;
namely, <hi>when they are received by faith;</hi> FOR THEY AD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MONISH
AND MOVE US TO BELEEVE AS THE WORD
DOTH: Therefore by his reſolution the Sacraments are converting Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances,
and meanes of begetting grace as well, and in like manner as the
Word, and not confirming Ordinances onely of grace begun. Yea, he
<note n="b" place="margin">Ibid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> loc. de Sacramento<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum numero.</note> poſitively affirmes, (and ſo did our Engliſh Apoſtle<note n="c" place="margin">Dialogorum l. 4. c. 1. f. 101. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>imiliter prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatio verbi<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Apoſtolici; Videtur eſſe Sacramentum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o quod eſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ignum ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis auditorii, &amp; ita ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canter in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ide Scripturae in jung <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> exerc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ium al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ius Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, &amp;c<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>John Wickliffe</hi> long
before him) That <hi>the very preaching of the Word is a Sacrament instituted in the
G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſpell<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Maximè autem placet mihi Ordinem, ut vocant, inter Sacramenta numerari,
mod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ut intelligatur ipſum ministerium Evangelii, &amp; voca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>io ad hoe ministerium do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendi
Evangelium &amp; adminiſtrandi Sacramenta, &amp;c<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Hoc modo numerare Ondinem inter
Sacr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>menta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fuerit utiliſſimum, ſcilicet, ad illustrandam dignitatem miniſteri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> verbi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>:</hi>
And he addes, That <hi>Prayer likewiſe may be called a Sacrament, becauſe it hath
great promiſes anne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed to it.</hi> If then Sacraments doe onely confirme grace
where it is begun before, not confirme and beget grace where it is wanting,
then by this new Divinity, neither the Miniſtry of the Word nor Prayer
ſhall be converting and regenerating, but onely confirming Ordinances<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
Since in <hi>Melanchtons</hi> and <hi>Wickliffes</hi> opinions (to omit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> others) they are
and may be called <hi>Sacraments</hi> as well as the <hi>Lords Supper</hi> or <hi>Baptiſme;</hi> which
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115480:20"/>
                  <hi>Wickliffe</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Dialogorum l. 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 1.</note> termes, <hi>primum Sacramentum</hi> CONFERENS GRATIA<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
PRIMAM SPIRITUALITER GENERANTEM: Aſſerting like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
in the ſame Chapter, <hi>Etſi diffinitio Sacramenti</hi> ſit, ſacrae rei ſignum, <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r
quod omne ſignabile ſit e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iam Sacramentum: Quià omnis creatura ſignat
ſuam creationem, &amp; etiam creatorem, &amp; ſic rem ſacram ſignat, &amp; Deus multas ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cras
creaturas ſignat &amp; ſeipſum: Quod</hi> ſi Sacramentum ſit inviſibilis gratiae vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibilis
forma, ut fimilitudinem gerat, &amp; cauſa exiſtat: <hi>Cum viſibilis forma in
propoſito ſignat quamcunque formam, vel quidditatem ſenſibilem; videtur, quod quaeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet
ſenſibilis creatura</hi> SIT ETIAM SACRAMENTUM, <hi>quia eſt viſibili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
ſorma inviſibilis gratiae creatoris, &amp; geret ſimilitudinem Idaearum, &amp; cauſa exiſtit ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudinis
ſuae, &amp; intelligentiae creaturis: Quomodo ſunt ergo ſolum ſeptem Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta
diſtincta ſpecivocè?</hi> Which I wiſh my Oppoſites to conſider, who ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance
the Sacraments ſo much above the Word w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> makes them Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts,
and appropriate the tilet of a Sacrament onely to Baptiſme and the Lords
Supper, from w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> they exclude and ſuſpend all ſcandalous perſons (&amp; their
children too from<note n="e" place="margin">Apology of the Churches in <hi>New-Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> againſt the exceptions of <hi>Richard Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> ch. 8. See Mr. <hi>Ruther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>furds</hi> due right of Presbyteries c. 4. ſect. 5 p. 221, &amp;c.</note> Baptiſme in <hi>New-England</hi>) upon pretence they are one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
confirming Ordinances, Sacraments and Seales of grace; upon which
pretext, they may as well ſuſpend them from the Miniſtry of the Word
and prayer, and from the uſe of any of Gods Creatures, which may
be termed Sacraments as well as theſe, if theſe two eminent Divines
miſtake not.</p>
               <p>I ſhall cloſe up this point with the reſolution of the whole Church of
<hi>England,</hi> both in the <hi>Articles of Religion,</hi> compiled and publiſhed in King
<hi>Edward</hi> the VI<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> his Reigne, Anno 1553. Artic. 26. refined and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
by Act of Parliament, Anno 1562. in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Reigne, Art.
25. <hi>of Sacraments;</hi> which determines thus: <hi>Sacraments ordained of Chriſt are
not onely badges and tokens of Chriſtian mens profeſſion, but rather, they be certaine
ſure witneſſes and</hi> EFFECTUALL SIGNES <hi>of Grace and Gods good will
towards us,</hi> by the which he doth WORKE INVISIBLY IN US, and
doth NOT <hi rend="sup">f</hi> ONELY QUICKEN,<note place="margin">The holy Spirit doth <hi>ſeale</hi> Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Eph. 1. 13 c. 4. 30. Rom. 8 10, 11. Yet it <hi>regenerats</hi> and <hi>converts them tos,</hi> John 3. 6. to 9. Rom. 8. 10, 11. 2 Cor. 3. 18. So doe the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments by its concurrence with them.</note> but ALSO STRENGTHEN
AND CONFIRME OUR FAITH IN HIM: Therefore by our own
Churches reſolution, which all our Miniſters have actually ſubſcribed to;
the Sacrament of Baptiſme, and the Lords Supper too, is both a converting
and regenerating Ordinance to quicken and beget, as well as a confirming
Ordinance to ſtrengthen and confirme grace; and ſo it is no <hi>New Paradox</hi> of
mine, but an ancient reſolved truth, yea the very received Doctrine of our
Church, and of the Churches of Chriſt in former Ages; and the contrary
opinion a meere upſtart errour, maintained purpoſely by ſome Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines
(againſt their owne ſubſcriptions, if not their conſciences too,)
to juſtifie and ſupport <hi>the ſole ſuſpention of ſcandalous perſons from the Lords
Supper, as a Divine inſtitution by the will and appointment of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> which
elſe would neceſſarily fall unto the ground, if this maine pillar of it be
ſubverted.</p>
               <p>As for Maſter <hi>Rutherfurds,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Objection 5.</note> Doctor <hi>Drak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> and others maine reaſon to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:115480:20"/>
the contrary, That <hi>no man can receive the Lords Supper worthily, unleſſe he come
unto it with a true lively faith, and ſincere repentance; which graces he cannot
enjoy without he be firſt really converted, elſe he eats and drinks dam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ation, not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion
to himſelfe: Ergo, This</hi> Sacrament is no firſt converting, but onely a
confirming Ordinance.</p>
               <p>I anſwer,<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> Firſt, that the argument is but a meere fallacy, which will ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
nullifie all Ordinances, or prove no Ordinance (no not the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of the Word or Prayer) to be converting, but meerly confirming; for
the very preaching of the Word will neither profit, nor externally nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
convert any that heare it, unleſſe they heare it with faith, as is reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
by Heb. 4. 2. <hi>But the Word preached did not profit them, not being mixed with
faith in them that heard it,</hi> &amp; Rom. 1. 16, 17. Heb. 11 4. 6. Mar. 16. 15, 16. 1 Pet. 2.
1, <hi>to</hi> 9. So <hi>Prayer without Faith is vain, ineffectuall, &amp; receiveth nothing from the Lord,</hi>
Jam. 1. 5, 6. ch. 5. 15. <hi>Ergo,</hi> by this reaſon (if allowed) a man muſt have ſaith
and ſpirituall life wrought in him before he can either heare or pray with
profit as he ought, and ſo muſt be firſt converted ere he can heare the Word
or Pray: What then ſhall we conclude hence, that men neither may nor
ought to pray, heare or receive the Lords Supper untill they be actually re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated
and inſpired with ſaving faith? God forbid; for then Godſhall
have no worſhip, and men no publick Ordinances: we muſt therefor
know, that God hath appointed both the Word, Sacraments and Prayer,
as the ordinary meanes or inſtruments whereby he begets true ſpirituall
life, faith and grace within us, by the effectuall concurrence of the ſpirit
in and with them; whereupon he frequently<note n="s" place="margin">Iſa. 55. 1, 2, 3. Pro. 8 32, 33, 34. c. 9. 3, 4, 5. c. 7. 1, 2, 3 James 1. 56, 7. 19, 18, 19, 21. 2 Tim. 2. 25, 26.</note> 
                  <hi>commands us, to reſort unto the
Ordinances with care and conſcience, to the end we may be convert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d, and quickened
by them when we want grace,</hi> as well as ſtrengthned or confirmed when we
have grace begun within us: Hence is that ſpeech of our Saviour, John 5.
21, 24, 25, 26. <hi>For as the Father raiſeth up the dead and quickneth them, even ſo
the Sonne quickneth whom he will: He that heareth my Word, and beleeveth on him
that ſent me, hath everlaſting life, and ſhall not come into condemnation: Verily, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily
I ſay uno you, the hou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e is comming and now is,</hi> THAT THE DEAD
(in ſinne and naturall corruption) SHALL HEARE THE
VOYCE OF THE SONNE OF GOD, AND THEY
THAT HEARE IT SHALL LIVE. Which is thus ſeconded, Eph.
2. 1. to 8. <hi>And you hath he quickned</hi> (to wit, by the Word and other Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances
accompanied with the Spirit) WHO WERE DEAD IN
TRESPASSES AND SINNES; <hi>But God who is rich in mercy, for
his great love wherewith he loved us,</hi> EVEN WHEN WEE WERE
DEAD IN SINNES HATH QUICKNED US <hi>together with
Chriſt, and hath raiſed us up together and made us ſit together in heavenly places in
Chriſt Jeſus, &amp;c. For by grace ye are ſaved through Faith, and that not of your
ſelves, it is the gift of God, &amp;c.</hi> a pregnant Text: As Chriſts ſpeech to
<hi>Lazarus</hi> lying dead and buried in his grave, <hi>to wit, Lazarus come forth;</hi> was
the inſtrumentall meanes both of his raiſing from the dead, and comming
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115480:21"/>
forth of the grave accordingly, <hi>John</hi> 11. 43, 44. And as his words to the
dead Rulers Daughter, Mark 5. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 42. <hi>Damoſell ariſe;</hi> and <hi>Peters</hi> ſpeech to
dead <hi>Tabitha,</hi> Acts 9. 40, 41. <hi>Tabitha ariſe,</hi> were the inſtrumentall meanes
and cauſe both of their raiſing and reviving; and as Gods command in
the very firſt creation, <hi>Let there be light, &amp;c.</hi> was the inſtrumentall cauſe of
creating light and all other creatures before they had a being:<note place="margin">Geneſis 1.</note> So the
Word, Sacraments and Prayer are Gods ordinary inſtruments whereby he
quickens thoſe who are dead in ſinnes, and begets ſaving faith with other
graces in ſuch who formerly never had them, by his Spirit working in
and by theſe meanes: Hence is that notable ſpeech of Chriſt to <hi>Paul,</hi> Acts
26. 17, 18. <hi>Now I ſend thee to the Gentiles, to open their eyes, and to turne them
from darkneſſe to light, and from the power of Satan unto God, that they may receive
forgiveneſſe of ſinnes, and inheritance among them that are ſanctified by faith that is
in me.</hi> Theſe Ordinances doe not find us living, worthy or regenerate,
but make us ſuch; doe not preſuppoſe faith and repentance already in us,
(for what ſhould work them?) but the contrary; and therefore are ordained
to beget faith and ſpirituall life <hi>even in thoſe who are dead in ſinnes,</hi> Mark 16.
15, 16. 2 Tim. 2. 25, 26. Acts 16. 14, 15. ch. 2. 37, 38. chap. 10. 44. Eph. 2. 1, &amp;c.
and after that, to confirme and ſtrengthen all ſpirituall graces wrought
within us; by meanes whereof, when wrought, the Ordinances which
firſt inſtrumentally begat them, become more profitable and comfortable
to us then before: This is ſo cleer, that Maſter<note n="t" place="margin">Due right of Presbyteries, c. 4. ſect. 5. p. 285, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Rutherfurd</hi> is forced to
confeſſe, That <hi>the Church may, nay ought to give the Sacraments of Baptiſme and
the Lords Supper, even to ſuch as are not truly regenerated, if they externally profeſſe
the Goſpell, as well as preach the Goſpell to them,</hi> (though contradicting himſelfe,
as I conceive, he affirmes<note n="v" place="margin">Which Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Rutherfurd</hi> affirmes, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine right of Church-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, p. 280.</note> elſwhere, That <hi>to come to the Lords Supper is not
commanded to all, not to Pagans, not to children, rot to the unregenerate,</hi> BUT
ONELY TO THE REGENERATED;) Of which no other
reaſon can be given, but that they are meanes of begetting, as well as en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing
grace, and converting as well as confirming Ordinances, from
which none who deſire them (if not actually excommunicated for obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
impenitency and contempt againſt the Ordinances) ought to be ſeclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
unleſſe naturall diſabilities hinder them.</p>
               <p>Hence<note n="w" place="margin">Concordia Lutherana p. 542. to 250.</note> 
                  <hi>Martin Luther</hi> in his Greater Catechiſme, exciting men by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
arguments to the frequent receiving of the Lords Supper, the <hi>neglect
whereof makes our devotion and love to Chriſt grow every day colder and colder, cauſeth
us at laſt-to grow bruitiſh,</hi> yea <hi>extreamly to conte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ne both the Sacrament and Word too,</hi>
as he there avers from his own experience (which I wiſh thoſe Divines who
put off and deny the Sacrament to their people for moneths, nay, yeers
together, would now at laſt conſider;) removes one maine Objection
which deterred many from the Sacrament (to wit, <hi>their owne unworthineſſe
ſinfulneſſe</hi> and <hi>unpreparedneſſe to receive it</hi>) with this encouraging argument;
<hi>That this Sacrament was not instituted for thoſe that are worthy, and purely cleanſed
from their ſinnes, but cloane contrary, even for miſerable and wretched ſinners, ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:115480:21"/>
of nothing but their owne unworthineſſe: Therefore let ſuch a one ſay, Lord, I
would very willingly be worthy of this Supper, but yet I come unto it induced by no wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe
of mine owne, but trusting on thy Word alone, becauſe thou haſt commanded me
to come, &amp;c. For the Sacrament is not to be looked upon as an hurtfull thing, from
which we ſhould run with both our feet, but as a ſaving and wholſome medicine, which
may heale thy diſeaſes, and give life both to thy ſoule and body: Why then doe we ſo
ſhun it, as if it were a poyſon</hi> (as ſome<note n="x" place="margin">Maſter <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therfurds</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine right of Church-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. pag 252, 253, 254 &amp;c. A brotherly &amp; friendly cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> p. 6, 7. An Antidote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt foure dangerous Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aeries, with others.</note> Divines now tearme it, to ſcarre peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
from it) <hi>which being received, would bring preſent death unto us?</hi> Yea, <hi>but ſome
may ſay; I am not ſo ſenſible of my ſinnes and unworthineſſe as I ſhould be: To ſuch as
are in this condition, I can give no better advice, then to looke into their owne hearts,
and to ſee whether they be not fleſh and blood, and may not ſay with</hi> Paul, Rom. 7. I
know that in me, that as in my fleſh dwelleth nothing that is good: <hi>In
ſumme, by how much the leſſe thou art throughly ſenſible of thy ſinnes and defects, the
more reaſons thou haſt of comming, and frequent ſeeking help and phyſick.</hi> The ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
whereof is but this: That the frequent receiving of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
is an effectuall meanes to<note n="y" place="margin">So the Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally hold. <hi>Hinkelman,</hi> de Anabaptiſmo, Diſp. 9. c. 1. Er. 6.</note> beget and work repentance, ſenſe of ſinne,
ſpirituall life, health, true grace within us when we want them, as well as
to encreaſe, confirme them when we have them; whence it is general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
tearmed by Divines, A MEANES OF GRACE; therefore we
muſt frequently reſort unto it in obedience to Gods command, as well
to obtaine faith, repentance and ſpirituall graces by and in it, when wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,
as to corroborate and augment them when wrought in us.</p>
               <p>Secondly, this Argument neceſſarily implies, that the Sacraments muſt
be adminiſtred to none but the Elect and truly regenerate: For ſince none
are endued with ſaving grace, faith, repentance, but onely the Elect, and
none ought to be admitted to the Sacraments but ſuch who are endued
with ſaving grace, faith, repentance, as the Objection concludes; It
inevitably followes, that none but the elect and perſons truly regenerate,
muſt be admitted to the Sacrament: But this the Objectors themſelves de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
and refute, both in the caſe of Baptiſme and the Lords Supper too:
Hence Maſter <hi>Rutherfurd</hi> determines in his Due Right of Presbyteries, ch.
4. ſect. 5. pag. 185. <hi>The Church may orderly and lawfully give the Seales of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
to thoſe to whom the Covenant and promiſes of grace doe not belong in Gods De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree
of Gods Election:</hi> refuting the contrary opinion as Anabaptiſticall:<note n="x" place="margin">Defence of Infant Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme. part 3.</note> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
<hi>Marſhall</hi> doth the like, and that upon theſe grounds:</p>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe Chriſt and his Apoſtles admitted divers to Baptiſme and
the Lords Supper, who were never elect or truly regenerate, as <hi>Judas, Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
Magus,</hi> and others. Secondly, becauſe no Miniſters without ſpeciall
revelation, but<note n="y" place="margin">2 Chron. 6. 33. 2 Tim. 6. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>God alone infallibly know who are Elect and truly regenerate,</hi>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">Jer. 17<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 9.</note> 
                  <hi>the
hearts of men bring deceitfull aboue all things,</hi> and<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 22. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>many called, but few cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
and ſo they cannot tell certainly who to admit, or who to ſeclude from
the Sacrament: Upon which ground Maſter<note n="b" place="margin">Defence of Infant Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme p 111. &amp; 140.</note> 
                  <hi>Marſhall</hi> himſelfe concludes
thus againſt Maſter <hi>Tombes:</hi> And <hi>truly Sir, whoſoever will grant that a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
in applying the Seale, muſt doe it</hi> de fide, <hi>in faith, being ſure he applies it accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:115480:22"/>
to rule, muſt either grant ſuch a right as I plead for, that many have right to be
viſible members, and be partakers of the externall administration of Ordinances,
though they be not inwardly ſanctified; or elſe he muſt by revelation be able to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ee and
know the inward converſion of every one he applies the Seales unto, for certainly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
hath no written word to build his Faith upon, for the ſtate of this or that man:</hi> And
<hi>for my owne part, when once you have diſproved this, that there is ſuch a viſible mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſhip
and right to externall Administrations as I have here inſisted upon, I ſhall not
onely forbeare baptizing Infants,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Note.</note> 
                  <hi>but the Administration of the outward ſeale to any,
what profeſſion ſoever they make, untill I may be</hi> de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ide <hi>aſſured that they are inwardly
regenerate.</hi> Thirdly, becauſe Chriſt hath ordained the Sacraments to be
<hi>means of distinguiſhing Christians from Pagan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> yea, to be an accidentall means of
<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Cor. 11. 27 28, 29. 2 Cor. 2. 25, 26. Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> Art. 29.</note> 
                  <hi>aggravating mens ſin, ingratitude, damnation, and to leave thoſe without excuſe who
unworthily receive them,</hi> which end ſhould be wholly fruſtrated, if unregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
Chriſtians ſhould be ſecluded from them; therefore this argument
which ſubverts our Oppoſites owne Tenet, and with the Anabaptiſts ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>popriates
the adminiſtration of the Sacraments to the Elect alone, muſt
wholly be exploded as falſe and dangerous.</p>
               <p>Wherefore the Objectors muſt be driven of neceſſity to renounce this
Objection, together with that of<note n="c" place="margin">In cap. 4. 2d Rom. p<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 39. 2. &amp; Explic. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tech. qu. 81. Art. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Paraeus,</hi> which ſeduced them, <hi>Sacramenta
non ſunt instituta justificandis, ſed justificatis; hoc eſt non infidelibus, ſed converſis;</hi>
which if meant onely of perſons inwardly converted, is an errour; if of
Pagans not converted, as he perchance meanes it, is quite miſtaken by the
Oppoſites.</p>
               <p>Finally,<note place="margin">Objection 6.</note>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">See Maſter <hi>Rutherfurds</hi> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vine right of Church-go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, c. 5 qu. 1. p. 242<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 243. &amp;c. 15.</note> they object. <hi>That the Priests were to put difference between holy and
unholy, between uncleane and cleane,</hi> Levit. 10. 10. Hag. 2. 11, 14, and that
they are checked by God himſelfe, Ezek. 22. 26. <hi>for putting no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
the holy and prophane, the uncleane and cleane: Ergo,</hi> Church-officers and
the Miniſters of the Goſpell have power by the will and appointment
of Jeſus Chriſt, not onely to excommunicate, but likewiſe to ſuſpend
ſcandalous and ignorant perſons from the Lords Supper.</p>
               <p>I anſwer,<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> that the Argument is a meere Nonſequitur: For firſt, theſe
Texts belong only to the <hi>Aaronicall Priests</hi> under the Law,<note n="e" place="margin">Heb. 7. 11. to the end, &amp;c. 8<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; 9. &amp; 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Aboliſhed by Chriſt,</hi>
not to the Miniſters of the Goſpell: Secondly, they ſpeak onely of c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall
<hi>Holin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and prophanneſſe, cleanneſſe and uncleanneſſe,</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Acts 10. 10. to 17. Col. 2. 14. to 23. 1 Tim. 4. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>abrogated by
Chriſt,</hi> not of morall: Thirdly, not of perſons morally holy or unholy,
cleane or uncleane; but rather of me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts, or creatures ceremonially holy
and unholy, clean and uncleane, or at leaſtwiſe of perſons, meats and crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
promiſcuouſly, only as ceremonially clean &amp; uncleane: Fourthly, the
<hi>putting of difference</hi> here mentioned, was not any actuall ſecluding unclean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
perſons from the Paſſeover or Lords Supper, or ſuſpending them from all
publick Ordinances by any judiciall power veſted in the Prieſts, but onely
the Prieſts inſtructing of the people what was holy and unholy, clean and
uncleane, as is evident by Levit. 10. 10. <hi>That ye may put difference between ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
and unholy</hi> (things) <hi>uncleane and cleane</hi> (things:) But how was this to be
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:115480:22"/>
done? Onely by inſtruction, as the next words manifeſt; <hi>And that ye may
teach the children of Iſrael all the Statutes which the Lord hath commanded them by
the hand of</hi> Moſes; (<hi>viz.</hi> concerning the holy and unholy, uncleane and
cleane creatures, mentioned in <hi>Levit. 10. &amp; Deut.</hi> 14.) compared with <hi>Ezek.</hi>
22. 26. <hi>Her Prieſts have broken my Law, and have defiled my holy things, they have
put no difference between the holy and prophane, neither have they ſhewed the difference
between the uncleane and the cleane:</hi> and <hi>Ezek.</hi> 44. 23. And THEY SHALL
TEACH MY PEOPLE THE DIFFERENCE BETWEEN THE
HOLY AND PROPHAN<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, AND CAUSE THEM TO DIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CERNE
BETWEEN THE UNCLEANE AND THE CLEANE:
So that the Prieſts <hi>putting difference between holy and unholy, cleane and uncleane</hi> in
<hi>Lev.</hi> 10. 10. is both by the t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nth verſe, and theſe Texts of <hi>Ezekiel</hi> expreſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted
to be nothing elſe, but a <hi>teaching or ſhewing the children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>to put
a difference and to diſcerne between the holy and prophane, unclean and clean things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed
by the ceremoniall Law;</hi> not a judiciall power or Eccleſiaſticall juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction
to excommunicate unholy and uncleane perſons from the publick
Ordinances, or ſociety of the holy and cleane, much leſſe a power to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend
them onely from the Paſſeover or Lord Supper, as is pretended by
the Objectors: This I ſhall further cleer by <hi>Haggai</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 11, 12, 13. the place
objected: <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, Aske now the Prieſts concerning the Law,
ſaying, If one beare holy fleſh in the skirt of his garment, and with his skirt doe touch
bread, or pottage, or wine, or any meat, ſhall it be holy? and the Prieſts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nſwered,
No: Then ſaid</hi> Haggai, <hi>if one that is uncleane by a dead body touch any of theſe, ſhall
it be</hi> UNCLEANE? <hi>And the Prieſt, anſwered and ſaid, It ſhall be</hi> UN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CLEANE:
And by Levit. 20. 25, 26. <hi>Ye ſhall therefore</hi> PUT DIF<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FERENCE
<hi>between</hi> CLEAN AND UNCLEAN BEASTS,
<hi>and between</hi> UNCLEANE FOWLES AND CLEANE, &amp;c.
<hi>And ye ſhall be holy unto me, for I the Lord am holy:</hi> and Levit. 11. 46, 47. where
after God had made a large deſcription what <hi>fleſh, Birds and Beaſts were cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monially
uncleane and not to be eaten by the Iſraelites, and what cleane and to be ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en
by them,</hi> he concludes thus; <hi>This is the Law of Beaſts, and of Fowles, and of every
living thing that moveth in the waters, and of every thing that creepeth upon the earth,</hi>
THAT YE MAY PUT A DIFFERENCE (not the Prieſts)
<hi>between the uncleane and cleane, and between the Beaſts that may be eaten, and the
Beaſts that ought not to be eaten:</hi> If then this be the genuine meaning of theſe
Texts, as is cleer in my apprehenſion by paralelling them together, then all
the argument that can be thence deduced is but this inconſequent:</p>
               <p>The Aaronicall Prieſts were to teach the people to put a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
Beaſts, Fowles, Meats that were cleane and uncleane, and between
things holy and unholy by the Leviticall Law.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> Presbyters and Presbyteries under the Goſpell, have a judiciall
Eccleſiaſticall authority veſted in them by the will and appointment of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
Chriſt, to ſuſpend ignorant and ſcandalous perſons from the Lords
Supper, and excommunicate obſtinate ſinners from the Church and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
Ordinances.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:115480:23"/>
What ill logick, ſenſe and coherence is in this argument, I referre to
the meaneſt capacity to determine: Yet this is all theſe Scriptures yeeld
our Oppoſites for proofe of excommunication or ſuſpention, though they
much inſiſt upon them; they might as well, or rather better argue hence,
that the people themſelves, not the Prieſts, ought to excommunicate or
ſuſpend ſcandalous perſons from the Lords Supper, becauſe the <hi>people were
to put a difference between creatures cleane and uncleane, and the Prieſts themſelves
were but to teach the people to put the difference between the holy and unholy, cleane and
uncleane, as theſe Texts reſolve;</hi> the rather, for that the Apoſtle <hi>Jude</hi> in his Epiſtle
verſe 1, 22, writes to all <hi>Chriſtians who are called and ſanctified</hi> (not to Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
and Presbyteries) <hi>to have compaſſion of ſome,</hi> MAKING A DIFFE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RENCE,
<hi>and others to ſave with feare, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fiftly, admit the Prieſts had power to put a difference between holy
and unholy, cleane and uncleane perſons as well as Beaſts, by vertue of
theſe Texts, as is pretended; yet <hi>putting a differerence</hi> is no infallible proofe
of a power veſted in them (much leſſe in the Miniſters of the Goſpell or
Presbyteries) to excommunicate unholy or uncleane perſons, or ſuſpend
ſcandalous or ignorant ones from the Lords Supper onely, ſince every pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate
Chriſtian is to put a difference between ſpiritually holy and uncleane
perſons, and thoſe that are morally unholy and uncleane; yet it followes
not thereupon that he may judicially excomm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>icate or ſuſpend them from
the Sacrament; the Miniſters and private Chriſtians muſt put a differente
between ſuch as theſe: Firſt, in their affections and eſteem of them; they
muſt<note n="g" place="margin">John 13. 34, 35. Eph. 1 15 c. 5. 2. 1 John 3. 11, 14. Pſal. 15. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>love and honour the one,</hi> but<note n="h" place="margin">2 Chron. 19 2. Pſal. 15. 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Pſal 139 21, 22. Prov 29. 27. 2 Kings 3 13, 14.</note> 
                  <hi>hate and diſreſpect the other:</hi> Secondly, in their
carriage towards them, <hi>they muſt</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">Titus 1. 13. c 2. 15. Luke 13 3, 5. Levit 19 17. Eph 5. 11</note> 
                  <hi>admoniſh and ſharply rebuke the one, denou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
Gods judgements againſt their ſins,</hi> but<note n="k" place="margin">Iſa. 41. 1, 2. Col. 3. 16. Gal 6. 1, 2.</note> 
                  <hi>exhort, encourage and comfort the other
with Gods promiſes;</hi> they muſt<note n="l" place="margin">Pſal. 16. 3. Pſal. 101. 6. Acts 2. 44, 44,</note> 
                  <hi>familiarly converſe with, and lovingly embrace
and delight in the company of the one,</hi> but avoid all<note n="m" place="margin">1 Cor. 5. 9, 10, 11. 2 Theſ 3. 14. 2 John 10, 11. Tit. 3. Pſal. 101. 4, 7, 8.</note> 
                  <hi>familiar converſation and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timacy
with the other:</hi> Such a putting of difference as this between holy and
unholy we admit of, but any other then this, is no wayes warranted from
theſe objected Texts.</p>
               <p>I ſhall therefore conclude from all the Premiſes (till convinced by bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
Scripture Authorities, Arguments, Reaſons, then ever I could yet meet
with in any Forraigne or Domeſtick <hi>Writers;</hi>) That <hi>Suſpention of ſcandalous
perſons from the Lords Supper onely, who deſire to receive it, without excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
them from all other publick Ordinances and Chriſtian ſociety,</hi> though it be
ſomewhat ancient in the Church, introduced, preſcribed at firſt by <hi>the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous</hi>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">See Concil. Ancyranum, can. 5, 6, 7, 8. Nicaenum 1. can. 11, 12, 13. Eliberinum can. 1, 2, 3. A relatenſe 2. can. 11, 12. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Laur. Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam. Concil. Tom 1.</note> 
                  <hi>of certaine Councils, in ſpeciall caſes of Apoſtacy in times of perſecution,</hi> as a
<hi>meere Eccleſiaſticall puniſhment of humane inſtitution,</hi> as the Canons themſelves
demonſtrate (which ſeem very unreaſonable or fictitious) and<note n="o" place="margin">De Rebus Eccleſiaſt. cap. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llafri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus
Strabo</hi> intimates, who termes it, <hi>A ſanctis Patribus conſtitutum,</hi> a conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of the Fathers, not of Chriſt; (in which ſenſe I oppugne it not, nor as
preſcribed by the Parliament in a prudentiall way) yet it is no <hi>Divine Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
or Inſtitution; and that there is no power to inflict any ſuch ſuſpention veſted in
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:115480:23"/>
Miniſters, Presbyteries, or Church-Officers by the will and appointment of Jeſus
Chriſt revealed in the Scripture,</hi> as many now moſt confidently averre both in
Preſſe and Pulpit, without any ſolid reaſon or authority to juſtifie their
aſſertion.</p>
               <p>Wherefore conſider ſeriouſly what I have written, and the Lord give
us underſtanding in all things, that we may no longer diſturbe the peace
both of Church and State with any groundleſſe <hi>pretended divine Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures</hi>
and <hi>Juriſdictions,</hi> which Chriſt never exerciſed, nor inſtituted in his
Church, nor deprive the people of thoſe divine repaſts at the Lords Table,
which ſhould be frequently adminiſtred to them for their converſion, edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication
and ſpirituall conſolation, upon meer new crochets and grounds
of conſcience, never once inſiſted on heretofore, till this new project of
claiming an Eccleſiaſticall power of ſuſpention from the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
onely, by <hi>the will and appointment of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> was ſet on foot; but reſt
ſatisfied with the Apoſtles reſolution and councell, with which I ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude,
Rom. 14. 16, 17, 18, 19. <hi>Let not then your good be evill ſpoken of; for
the Kingdome of God is not meat and drink</hi> (I may adde, nor yet Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
nor ſuſpention from the Lords Supper, as ſome now make it) <hi>but righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe,
and peace, and joy in the holy Ghoſt; for he that in theſe things ſerveth Chriſt is
acceptable to God and approved of men; let us therefore follow after the things which
make for peace, and things wherewith one may edifie another;</hi> not domineer or ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannize
one over another, and the Lords Supper too.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alenſis Summa Theol.</hi> par. 4. qu. 22. mem. 1. Art. 4. Pluribus conceditur clavis
abſolutionis, quàm gladius excommunicationis; quiâ pauci ſunt qui ſciunt
hoc enſe percutere; undè propter periculum, paucorum manibus tradi
debet.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Page 1. line 8. dele <hi>one.</hi> p 4 l 20, for 2 read 9. l 36, for 37 r 33: p 5 l 40, <hi>thruſt ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
p 7 l 3, for, <hi>or.</hi> p 11 l 31, <hi>Churches.</hi> p 12 l 44, <hi>unfit.</hi> p 13 l 44, dele <hi>a.</hi> p 23 l 27, <hi>Charters.</hi>
p 25 l 42, the, <hi>to:</hi> p 27 l 33, <hi>conferunt.</hi> l 44, all, <hi>many.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Margin. p 5 l 2, 23 r 29. l 10, 179, r 278.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
